<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure sermons The two first, of godly feare: on Hebrewes 4. verse 1. By Robert Cleauer. The two last. Of Christian loue and life. On Canticles 2. verse 10. By Richard Webb.</title>
            <author>Cleaver, Robert, 1561 or 2-ca. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108059</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8504</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8504)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1406:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure sermons The two first, of godly feare: on Hebrewes 4. verse 1. By Robert Cleauer. The two last. Of Christian loue and life. On Canticles 2. verse 10. By Richard Webb.</title>
                  <author>Cleaver, Robert, 1561 or 2-ca. 1625.</author>
                  <author>Webb, Richard, preacher of God's word. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 [i.e. 39], [7], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Snodham, for Roger Iackson, and are to be sould at his shop neere to Fleetstreet Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Two sermons. Of Christian loue and life" by Richard Webb has separate pagination and dated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>P. 39 (first series) misnumbered 40.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8504:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8504:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FOVRE SERMONS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The two firſt,</hi> OF GODLY FEARE: On <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 4. <hi>Verſe</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Cleauer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The two last.</hi> Of Chriſtian Loue and Life. On <hi>Canticles</hi> 2. <hi>Verſe</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Webb.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Chronicles 15.2.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lord is with you while you be with him.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by THO. SNODHAM, for ROGER IACKSON, and are to be ſould at his ſhop neere to Fleetſtreet Conduit 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8504:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8504:2"/>
                  <head>THE FIRST SERMON: OF GODLY FEARE.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>HEBREVVES 4. VERSE 1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Let vs feare therefore, leaſt at any time, by forſaking the promiſe of entring into his reſt, any of you ſhould ſeeme to be depriued.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe wordes doe depend vpon the former Chapter; where the writer of this Epiſtle propoſeth vnto the HE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BREVVES the example of their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, ſhewing how they rebelled in the wilderneſſe, and hardned their hearts, and refuſed to yeeld obedience vnto the word of the Lord, for which cauſe he ſwore that they ſhould not enter into his reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> into the land of Canaan; and therein vvas as good as his word; for they all periſhed in the wilderneſſe. The like hee declareth to haue fallen out in the time of <hi>Dauid, to wit,</hi> that they refuſed to hearken vnto Gods voyce, and therefore were excluded from the heauenly reſt, albeit they inhabited the land of CANAAN, which was a Type thereof. Herevpon the Apoſtle enforceth an exhortation by way of application, wherein we may obſerue:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8504:3"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Firſt, the duties which they ought to looke vnto, which are theſe two:
<list>
                              <item>1 Firſt, to the intent they may not be like the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Iſraelites, they muſt get an holy feare into their hearts.</item>
                              <item>2 Secondly, they muſt lay holde of the promiſe, and not forſake or reiect the ſame.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 Secondly, the reaſons to moue them therevnto, which are alſo two:
<list>
                              <item>1 The firſt whereof is taken from the miſerable ſucceſſe of them that were formerly diſobedient, <hi>to wit,</hi> that their carkaſſes fell in the wilderneſſe, <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 3.17. <hi>Let vs feare [therefore,]</hi> that is, conſidering what ſinnes they committed, and what fearefull iudgements they incurred, let vs looke better to our ſelues.</item>
                              <item>2 The ſecond is drawen from the danger that would enſue vnto themſelues, if they did not follow his exhortation; they might ſeeme to be depriued of that reſt which God promiſed vnto his people.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let vs, &amp;c.]</hi> Here we may note whom he doth admoniſh, in this word <hi>[vs]</hi> which importeth thus much: let vs He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes; let me that am the writer of this Epiſtle; let all that are in CHRIST IESVS, euen euery one of vs, <hi>feare, &amp;c.</hi> Now, in that hee ioynes himſelfe with thoſe, to whom hee giues this caueat, the Doctrine is, that</p>
                  <p>Hee that doth faithfully inſtruct others,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> will alſo inſtruct himſelfe with his owne precepts.
<note place="margin">Faithfull Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers will teach themſelues. Rom. 1.23.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The neglect of this, is greatly condemned by the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> who ſpeaketh vnto the Iewes in this manner; <hi>Thou that teachest another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelfe? and thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteale, doſt thou ſteale? &amp;c.</hi> In which place he ſheweth that it is a fearefull and inexcuſeable ſinne for a man to take vpon him to be an informer of others, and in the meane time to be vtterly vntaught himſelfe, in reſpect of any working and ſauing inſtruction; neither was this holy Apoſtle more ready to cenſure the omiſſion of this duty in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8504:3"/>others, than he was carefull to practiſe it himſelfe: for 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. hee ſaith; <hi>Let vs clenſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, and grow vp vnto full holineſſe, in the feare of God:</hi> where wee ſee that hee maketh himſelfe one of the number. So alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. when hee dilates at large of the corruption that is inherent in mans nature, he ſtill layes load vpon himſelfe, and ſpeakes as if no body were in ſuch caſe as he was. <hi>What I would</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that doe I not,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.15.</note> but what I hate, that doe I:</hi> and Ver. 18. <hi>I know that in me,</hi> that is, <hi>in my fleſh, there dwelleth no good thing:</hi> and Ver. 24. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</hi> And as in the matter of humiliation, ſo likewiſe in the matter of conſolation hee ſpeaketh in his owne perſon, ſeeking to apply the comfort to himſelfe, as well as to offer it vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; <hi>I thanke God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> v. 25. <hi>q.d.</hi> He it is that muſt deliuer me, and all his elect from the bondage of ſinne, and that by Ieſus Chriſt, for which I render humble and heartie praiſes vnto his Diuine Maieſtie. And againe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21. he ſaith; <hi>Chriſt is to me both in life and in death ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage.</hi> So that in matters of exhortation and of inſtruction, of humiliation and of conſolation, hee includeth himſelfe within the number of thoſe with whom hee hath to deale. And it ſtands with reaſon that Miniſters and Gouernors, and all ſuch as are to admoniſh others, ſhould take this courſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe their need requireth it:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> for haue not they (as well as others) corruption in them, that needs to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed? haue not they many failings that ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? haue not they much diffidence and diſtruſt in them, againſt which they muſt be ſtrengthned? If it fare thus with them, as none can deny, meet it is that they ſhould take their part with others, when they eyther reproue, or exhort, or comfort, or the like: and indeed, the Lord allots them a portion, together with the reſt of his ſeruants, euen as good houſeholders doe allow their Baker, and Bruer, and Cooke, and other officers, that makes prouiſion for the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, their ſtint of vittailes as farre foorth as any other, for whom they prepare the foode.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8504:4"/>
                  <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> this is a great incouragement and ſingular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto them that are inſtructed, or exhorted, &amp;c. to cauſe them to make vſe of that which is ſpoken, when they ſee men to take vp the like burdens themſelues, as they lay vpon their ſhoulders, and that they doe not deale hypocritically, as the Phariſes did, who impoſed heauy burdens vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when as they themſelues would not ſo much as touch them with one of their fingers. This, I ſay, makes mens words to be regarded and followed, when they require no more of others then they labour to doe themſelues; when they miniſter no medicines vnto others, but they will firſt take them themſelues: and on the contrary part this cauſeth men to be eſteemed Phyſitians of no worth, when they will take vpon them to cure others of thoſe faults, which they neuer ſeeke any redreſſe or reformation of in themſelues. He that will make boaſt that he hath a ſoueraigne remedie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Stone, or the Gowre, or any the like maladie, and yet in the meane time be miſerably tormented with the ſame himſelfe, ſhall cauſe both himſelfe, and his skill, to be little ſet by.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> it is dangerous and burdenous for mens ſoules not to ioyne themſelues with thoſe whom they doe inſtruct: for the things which they deliuer are eyther true or falſe: If falſe, how dare they propoſe them vnto others for feare of infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and poyſoning? If they be true, how can they but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, and make vſe of them in their owne ſoules, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they will haue their owne ſpeeches to be brought in as witneſſes againſt themſelues, and their owne admonitions to be as ſo many conuictions of themſelues to be altogether vnteachable and vntractable?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly and laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> they doe not onely hurt their owne ſoules, but hereby they much diſhonour God, and diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage his ſeruants. For let them perſwade men to be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to be liberall, to doe good vnto all, and hurt vnto none, &amp;c. The anſwere of many wilbe this: you Miniſters, or you Parſons of the Goſpell, can giue good words, but where are your deedes? Such and ſuch we haue heard to deliuer as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8504:4"/>ſound exhortations as you doe, and yet (God knowes) they come ſhort enough in their practize. You can tell vs that wee muſt be mercifull, &amp;c. but ſurely there are none more rauenous then you Preachers: for there are many of you that will neuer be ſatisfied, but would heape together a whole world of liuings if you could get them. Thus is the name of God blaſphemed through ſuch mens looſeneſſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the Lord forbid them to take his word into their mouthes, that caſt it behinde their backes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> and hate to be reformed thereby. Holy ſpeeches are vtterly vnbeſeeming vnholy perſons, neither will the Lord hold them guiltleſſe, that doe in ſuch ſort take his glorious Name in vaine.</p>
                  <p>Therefore let vs in our exhortations before wee ſpeake,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> ſeriouſly be-thinke our ſelues what wee are to ſpeake, and as farre as poſſibly wee can, labour to digeſt it before hand. Let vs be ſo teachers of others, that we be alſo learners our ſelues. If we haue matters of ill newes and of terrour to deliuer, let vs not vtter them as if they did not concerne vs, nor throw the threatnings of God abroad as durtes, whereof wee our ſelues are nothing at all afraid: but let vs ſtriue to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly moued and affected therewith, euen as the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> was with thoſe things vvhich were reuealed vnto him. <hi>When I heard</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my belly trembled, my lips ſhooke at thy voice: rottenneſſe entred into my bones, and I trembled in my ſelfe, that I might rest in the day of trouble.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hab. 3.16.</note> We ſhould be ſo farre from denouncing the iudgements of God in malice and diſtemper againſt the parties, that we ſhould endeauour throughly to affect our owne hearts with feare and griefe, before we vtter them vnto others. And the like may be ſaid for inſtructions, or conſolations, which we are about to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto any, we muſt in the firſt place make our owne vſe thereof.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, this is for the condemnation of thoſe that are appointed to be teachers of others, and yet none more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught than they: who are ſet as ſhepheards ouer Chriſt his ſheepe, and yet are themſelues as ſheepe without a ſhepheard, becauſe they are not ſhepheards vnto themſelues, as all good
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8504:5"/>Miniſters ought to be. Thence it commeth to paſſe, that albeit they giue others many good leſſons concerning mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and humilitie, and patience, and the like, yet none are more cruell, none more proud, none more reuengefull then they.</p>
                  <p>And ſo in families, many gouernors are to be rebuked, who are very hot and violent in dealing againſt the faults of their ſeruants, and children, without any conſideration of that like in themſelues: whereas euery reproofe which they giue vnto their inferiours, ſhould put them in minde of thoſe offences which either they haue committed, to be humbled for them, or which they may committe, to take greater heede of them, and to pray more earneſtly againſt them. And as for rebukes, ſo for chaſtiſements, they ſhould neuer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect either childe, or ſeruant, but they ſhould lay ſharper ſtroakes vpon their owne hearts for their tranſgreſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, than they doe vpon their bodies for their offences againſt them. Thus if they could doe, they might reape profit by euery fault which is committed, and by euery reproofe and correction which they giue for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let vs therefore feare.]</hi> This is the firſt duty vvhich they were to performe for the preuenting of thoſe euils which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell the ſtiffe-necked and rebellious Iſraelites, and for the keeping of themſelues in a better courſe than they tooke, whence this doctrine may be collected, that,</p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer will conſtantly cleaue vnto the LORD in a good way,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label>
                     <note place="margin">Godly feare very needfull.</note> muſt awe his heart with an holy feare.</p>
                  <p>Therefore is it that wee are commaunded to <hi>ſerue the Lord in feare,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.11.</note> and to reioyce before him with trembling.</hi> Whence we ſee that all the ſeruices of God, euen our reioycings and thankſgiuings, muſt be mingled with an holy feare. The like exhortation is giuen in another <hi>Pſalme,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> Tremble, and ſinne not;</hi> thereby implying that except men doe ſo, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Now the reaſons why thoſe that will ſtand in vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                     </label> muſt be affected with a religious feare, are theſe:</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe that is an excellent meanes to preſerue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8504:5"/>them from falling; for it ſheweth them the perill of ſinne, and breedeth in them a deteſtation thereof; it cauſeth them to diſcerne an hooke in Satans baytes, when he ſeemeth to proffer vnto them a good morſell: it maketh them to ſee that there is a net ſpread for them, when carnall delights are preſented vnto them: and therefore is it that Gods ſeruants doe ſtand in awe of thoſe puniſhments that are appointed for the workers of iniquitie,
<note place="margin">Iob 31.</note> euen when they are tempted vnto any euill, though neuer ſo ſecret; and by that meanes are preſerued from dangerous falles, when ſuch as are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of this feare of God, doe runne headlong into grieuous ſinnes, and ſo plunge themſelues ouer head and eares in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduoideable, and yet intollerable woes and miſeries.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as the feare of the Lord is a ſoueraigne preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue to keep: men from falling; ſo is it an excellent helpe to reſtore them when once they haue fallen. For that will cauſe them ſeriouſly to conſider what arrerages they haue runne into, and what a dangerous caſe they are in, and ſo to beſtirre themſelues with all ſpeede and with all diligence to get out of the ſame; euen as one that perceiues he hath taken Ratſ-bane, or any deadly poyſon, will haſten to the Phyſition, and vſe all meanes that may be to free himſelfe from that danger wherein he ſtandeth.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as this ſanctified feare will reſtraine and recouer vs from euill practiſes, ſo will it driue vs forward vnto holy duties, and make vs breake through all inconueniences, and troubles, and oppoſitions, that would otherwiſe hinder vs from the ſame. This holy feare will ouercome all fleſhly feares, and cauſe vs to perſiſt in good wayes,
<note place="margin">Ier. 32.40.</note> according to that of the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> who bringeth in the LORD, ſpeaking thus; <hi>I will put my feare in their hearts, and they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> No outward dangers can withdraw them from obedience; neither can any manner of difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties hinder them from proceeding in good courſes: Gods voice is more forcible to make them goe on, than all the threatnings of men can be to ſtay them: and therefore thoſe that doe more dread mens words than the Lords, deale as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8504:6"/>abſurdly, as if they ſhould be more terrrified at the barking of a Curre that ſtands in the way againſt them, than of the voyce of a Lyon that purſueth them at the heeles to teare them in pieces, if they haſten not forward: or as if they ſhould be more afrayd of a childe that threatneth to ſtrike them, if they paſſe by him, than of a man of Warre that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth cloſe after them to ſmite them with a ſword, if they goe not ſpeedily on their way. The holy men of God haue beene otherwiſe affected;
<note place="margin">1 King. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Micaih</hi> was more fearefull of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Lord, than of diſpleaſing <hi>Ahab.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw that God was angry with him for his carnall reaſoning againſt the Lords ſending of him vnto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 4.14.18.</note> he left off diſputing, and choſe rather to aduenture vpon any perill, than vpon Gods diſpleaſure. When <hi>Ieremy</hi> was threatned by the Lord,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 1.</note> that if he would not deliuer his meſſage, hee ſhould be deſtroyed, the Prophet had done, and durſt make no more obiections in his owne behalfe: ſo effectuall is this bleſſed and holy feare, whereſouer it is throughly rooted and ſetled in the heart.</p>
                  <p>Which maketh firſt for the reproofe of thoſe that liue in preſumption,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> and thinke it the beſt way to haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes performed vnto them, to be bolde and confident that they ſhall be performed, though in the meane time they walke on in the practiſe of notorious euils, and ſo haue no ground at all whereon to build this their falſe and fond ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination and perſwaſion. Wee haue a ſtrong faith in God (ſay they) and doe beleeue that he will be mercifull vnto vs, and therefore nothing ſhall feare vs; no, not the threatnings of the word that are denounced againſt vs: as who ſhould ſay, they are but words of courſe that ſhall neuer take effect: but what is this leſſe than to giue God the lye? for he ſayth that adulterers and vncleane perſons, and lyars, and raylers, ſhall not enter into the kingdome of Heauen: but they ſay, albeit we liue in theſe ſinnes, yet wee ſhall goe to Heauen notwithſtanding; what horrible preſumption is this? and how miſerable muſt they needs be all, whoſe hope depends on this, that it may be the Lord is miſtaken, and that his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8504:6"/>doings will at length be found contradictory to his words?</p>
                  <p>A ſecond vſe of this point may be to teach vs to get this holy feare of God into our hearts,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and for this end to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on the glorious Maieſtie of the Lord, and on his wonderfull iudgements executed vpon preſumptuous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp;c. whereby this affection may be begunne, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and increaſed in vs.
<note place="margin">On the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Whereof elſe-where more largely.</p>
                  <p>Let vs feare therefore; why? becauſe others prouoking the Lord were ſo grieuouſly plagued by him, let vs be made more wary through their example. Whence we may learne this doctrine, that the falles of others before vs, ſhould make vs to looke better to our owne ſtanding.</p>
                  <p>Other mens ſinnes and plagues muſt be ſo many admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and forewarnings vnto vs, to take heed of the like.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label>
                     <note place="margin">Other mens euils muſt make vs warie.</note> This the Apoſtle preſſeth in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where, hauing ſpoken of diuers particular offences of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, and of the ſeuerall puniſhments that were inflicted vpon them for the ſame, he maketh this concluſion, <hi>Now all theſe things came vnto them for exſamples,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.12.</note> and were written to admoniſh vs, vpon whom the ends of the world are come: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heede leaſt he fall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whence we ſee it euident, that when the Lord puniſhed the ſtubborne and rebellious Iſraelites in the deſert, hee did ayme at the good of all his Elect that ſhould liue in ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, and cauſed that Story to be written that all that ſhould reade it might make their vſe of it, and become more wary by their example; that they be not murmurers, idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, fornicaters, tempters of God, &amp;c. as they were, leaſt being found guilty of the ſame ſinnes, they pertake with them in the like puniſhments. In this very ſort alſo dealeth the Wiſeman in the <hi>Prouerbs;</hi> for, hauing ſhewed how dangerous and pernicious the entiſements and practiſes of the whoriſh woman are, hee thereupon inferreth,
<note place="margin">Pro. 7.25.26.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Let not thy heart decline to her: wander thou not in her pathes, for ſhe hath cauſed many to fall downe wounded:</hi> and leaſt any ſhould too farre preſume vpon his owne ſtrength, and ſo imagine that he ſhall eſcape
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8504:7"/>better than others haue done; hee addeth. <hi>The ſtrong men are all ſlaine by her. Her houſe is the way vnto the graue, which goeth downe to the chambers of death. q. d.</hi> It is euen like an houſe that is exceeding contagious, where few or none did euer eſcape if once they aduentured to come within the doores; and therefore as in that caſe euery man will be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to auoyd the place, and will not ſo much as paſſe by the doores, or come vnder the windowes, much leſſe thruſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in thither, where all that haue ventured to come in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, haue periſhed: ſo the holy Ghoſt aduiſeth vs with all diligence and due circumſpection to ſhun the occaſions of adulterie, and not to come neere the houſe of the adultereſſe, but to auoyd it, as the very portall vnto death, euen to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death, both of body and ſoule: and as <hi>Salomon</hi> gaue this in precept vnto others, ſo hee obſerued it in practiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;
<note place="margin">Pro. 24.30.31.</note> for ſeeing the field of the ſlothfull, and the Vineyard of the man deſtitute of vnderſtanding, to be all growne ouer with thornes and nettles, &amp;c. he marked it well, and receiued inſtruction. The ſight hereof made him more wiſe: for he conſidered that pouertie did vſually come vpon ſuch,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 3 2.</note> as a Poſte, and neceſſitie like an armed man, that is, ſpeedily and vnreſiſtibly, and therefore hee tooke the greater care to ſhake off idleneſſe and ſluggiſhneſſe, vpon which ſo great miſery doth attend, and will certainly enſue.</p>
                  <p>Now,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                     </label> let vs conſider why wee ought to take warning by other mens harmes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> there is the ſame corruption in vs, as there is in them; the vnfaithful and diſobedient Iſraelites that were conſumed in the Wilderneſſe; the men of the old world that periſhed by the floud; nay, the moſt vile Sodomites that were burnt to aſhes with Fire and Brimſtone from Heauen, had no worſe a nature than wee haue: for all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> haue drawne an equall portion of originall corruption from the loynes of their firſt Father. If then we be all of vs na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally alike inclinable vnto euill, why ſhould not wee ſeare by others falles, leaſt wee be ouertaken in the ſame ſort? <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</hi> that had carried himſelfe holily and chaſtely in <hi>Sodome,</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:8504:7"/>was a man very vnlikely (as wee would haue thought) to fall into inceſt, and to commit filthineſſe with his owne Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: yet ſuch vvas the vileneſſe of his nature, that by his Daughters meanes hee was drawen firſt vnto drunkenneſſe, and then vnto that other fowle and notorious euill before mentioned. And if ſuch a man as hee vvere ſo ſhamefully foyled, who can ſecure himſelfe from falling?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Sathan is the ſame now,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that heretofore hee hath beene: yea, and much more malicious becauſe he hath ſince then had a number of foyles, &amp; his time is ſtill ſhorter, in which regard hee is more imbittered and enraged, and therefore more violent in tempting vnto all manner of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: and haue not we then cauſe to tremble, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the falles of thoſe that haue gone before vs?</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the Lords threatnings denounced againſt ſinne,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> are the ſame ſtill, and the ſtrictneſſe of his iuſtice in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them is no whit diminiſhed: but as hee is conſtant in his goodneſſe towards ſuch as obey him, ſo is hee in his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe toward ſuch as diſobey him; and if there be any difference betwixt theſe our times, and the dayes of old, it ſtandeth herein, that thoſe that are offenders now, are likely to ſpeede worſe than thoſe of former times, becauſe they haue had their examples, vvhich ſhould haue made them more fearefull of prouoking the LORD, and yet haue not taken benefit thereby, but ruſhed vpon thoſe greiuous ſinnes, for which others haue beene much condemned, and ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed.</p>
                  <p>Let this therefore be an inſtruction vnto vs,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> that we ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider what breaches of the commaundements the Lord hath purſued with ſoreſt plagues heretofore, and ſo become watchfull ouer our owne hearts and wayes, that we be not found guiltie of the ſame:
<note place="margin">Nehem. 13, 17, 18.</note> thus did <hi>Nehemiah</hi> when he ſaw the Sabbath prophaned by the Iewes, <hi>Then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I reproued the Rulers of Iudah, and ſaid vnto them, what euill thing is this that ye doe, and breake the Sabbath day? Did not your fathers thus, and our God brought all this plague vpon vs, and vpon our Citie? Yet yee increaſe the wrath vpon Iſrael in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8504:8"/>breaking the Sabbath.</hi> In the ſame manner ſhould we reaſon: hath not the Lord ſmitten ſundry particular perſons in their eſtate for the prophaning of his holy reſt, beſides other ſtroakes that haue lighted vpon their bodies and ſoules? Nay hath he not brought vpon our whole Nation ſundry iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments euen for this haynous ſinne among many other? Why then ſhould wee perſiſt in prouoking him ſtill, and ſo pull downe vpon our heads one plague after another? So for the abuſing of the Lords ſupper, the Apoſtle ſaith, that many among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were ſmitten with weakeneſſe,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> and ſickneſſe, and with death it ſelfe: what vſe ſhould wee make thereof? Surely this: Did not they then eſcape Gods afflicting hand, that came vnpreparedly, and vnworthily, without examining and iudgeing of themſelues, vnto the holy Sacrament: then how can we expect to goe vnpuniſhed, if we pollute and defile that holy ordinance of God as they did?</p>
                  <p>The like may be ſaid of other ſinnes, as namely of thoſe wherewith the old world is charged,
<note place="margin">Luk. 17.26.27.</note> 
                     <hi>viz. That they eat, and dranke, and maried, and gaue in mariage, vnto the day that</hi> Noe <hi>entred into the Arke, and the floud came, and destroyed them all.</hi> That is, they liued in a profound worldlineſſe, being altogether careleſſe of heauenly matters, and ſetting their mindes vpon nothing, but the things of this life: they did traffique onely for their bodies, not at all for their ſoules. And was this ſo great a fault (will ſome ſay) for men to follow after their commodities and delights! Yes that they ſhould wholy giue ouer themſelues vnto the purſuite of theſe was ſo offenſiue vnto the Lord, that hee ſwept them all away by an vniuerſall deluge: they had ſo defiled the whole world, that it could not be throughly clenſed, till they were all waſhed away that were the offenders: And if wee follow them in thoſe carnall courſes, wee may iuſtly feare that the Lord will cut vs off, as hee did them, though not in the like manner: if we be men of the world and for the world, making it our whole life and the very end of our being here, to eate, and drinke, and buy, and ſell, and plant, and build: in a word, if
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8504:8"/>we be wholy addicted to our profit, and pleaſure and credit: and in particular for the matter of mariage, if wee looke wholy, or for the moſt part to perſonage, and portion, when wee are to make choiſe of yoake-fellowes for our ſelues and our children, not regarding vvhether they be Papiſts, or Atheiſts, or any manner of way prophane, ſo that they can ſatisfie our fleſhly affections for outward things; if (I ſay) we be thus diſpoſed, either wee ſhalbe cut off by an vntimely death, as the old world, and the Sodomites were, or if our dayes be prolonged, it ſhalbe to the increaſe of our woe and miſery, either in the time of our life, or after our death, or both. And whereas, concerning that former matter of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall matches, ſome may imagine, that albeit they mary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſant Papiſts, or others that are as bad, they can ſo order matters, that they will receiue no hurt by them, but bring them to Church, and ſo doe good vnto them, let them not preſume too much vpon their vaine conceits: <hi>Salomon</hi> was as wiſe as they: yet was not he able to conuert his Idolatrous wiues, but was himſelfe peruerted by them, and ſo haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moe beſide him.</p>
                  <p>Wee can be thus prouident for our bodily ſafety, that when wee ſee one to be ſwallowed vp in ſome griefe, or to periſh in a quick-ſand, or the like, wee will retire, and not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture vpon the perill: and ſurely the examples of Gods word, (though of things that haue beene acted many yeeres ſince) ſhould be more forcible to cauſe vs to ſhunne ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall dangers, than fearefull ſpectacles that are preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes ſhould be to make vs carefull of eſchewing corporall euils.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, in the ſecond place,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> here is a iuſt reproofe of thoſe that are ſo farre from being afraid at the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaults of their Anceſtors, that they are thereby much emboldned vnto wicked practiſes: of which number are all Papiſts, and ſundry els that are popiſhly minded: Oh (ſay they) this is an ancient religion, an ancient cuſtome, &amp;c. And what of that? Therefore let all Churches be defiled, and all particular perſons corrupted therewith: and ſo for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8504:9"/>the breaking of the Sabbath, it hath beene an vſuall thing time out of minde, (ſay they) and therefore why ſhould you finde fault with it? This is a bad argument: and if it might ſtand for a rule that the antiquity of a thing doth euer proue the lawfulneſſe thereof, what groſſe euill could be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as vnlawfull?</p>
                  <p>The Iſraelites hardning of their hearts in the wilderneſſe: the crying ſinnes of the Sodomites: the haynous offences of the old world; and the woefull diſobedience of our firſt Parents in Paradiſe, haue antiquitie for the maintenance of them, if that would ſerue the turne: but alas, that is ſo farre from making any fault alowable, that it cauſeth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitters thereof to be more in excuſeable, in as much as they haue not beene admoniſhed by the falls of ſuch as haue gone before them. Therefore let vs neuer beare our ſelues in hand that we may warrantably take this or that courſe of life, becauſe others haue done ſo before vs, vnleſſe wee can eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently proue out of the ſcriptures that they haue done well in ſo doing. Otherwiſe let vs rather feare (as in this text wee are exhorted) than preſume to walke in their ſteps. To God the Father, to Ieſus Chriſt his Sonne, and to the holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glory aſcribed both now and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8504:9"/>
                  <head>THE SECOND SERMON: OF GODLY FEARE.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>HEBREVVES 4. VERSE 1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Leaſt at any time, by forſaking the promiſe of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into his reſt, any of you ſhould ſeeme to be depriued.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>East at any time.]</hi> Theſe wordes doe ſhew the continuance of our watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, that it muſt be conſtant, not at ſome times alone, but at all times, whence obſerue this point, that,</p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer vvould attaine to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label>
                     <note place="margin">Conſtant vvatchfulneſſe required.</note> muſt ſtand conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perpetually vpon his guard, euery Chriſtian muſt keepe a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall watch ouer his owne ſoule; as well one day as another, as well hereafter, as for the preſent: there is no time of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or of interruption granted. Therefore is it that this ſame Apoſtle exhorteth, ſaying. <hi>Take heede, brethren,
<note place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note> leaſt [at any time] there be in any of you an euill heart, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, to depart away from the liuing God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 28.14.</note> And the vviſe man ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed is hee that feareth alwayes: but hee that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens his heart ſhall fall into euill.</hi> Implying thereby, that where this godly feare is at any time wanting, there that partie is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8504:10"/>prone to fall into hardneſſe of heart, and ſo to proceed from one wickedneſſe vnto another. The like caution is giuen by our Sauiour to his Diſciples, <hi>Take heede to your ſelues</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>leaſt [at any time] your hearts be oppreſſed with ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting,
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.34.</note> and drunkenneſſe, and the cares of this life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither is this vnceſſant watchfulneſſe more than needes:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
                     </label> for,</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the diuell goes about <hi>[continually] at a roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may deuoure.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.</note> Hee is as it were a ſtrong and cunning thiefe, that hath often marked euery place in our houſe where hee may breake in, and if wee haue not a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall eye vnto him, hee is ready to take vs at an aduantage, and to ſpoyle our ſoules of thoſe good things vvhich the Lord hath vouchſafed vnto vs: and when he is leaſt ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then is hee moſt induſtrious about his miſchieuous practiſes. Our warfare is different from that which earthly Princes doe exerciſe: for they are ſome times altogether without danger, but wee goe in continuall perill; wee know not how ſoone Sathan will be vpon vs; there is no moment wherein wee can ſecure our ſelues from his aſſaults; and if we be not euermore in a readineſſe to award off his blowes, we are likely to receiue a deadly wound.</p>
                  <p>Yea,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vvee haue not onely our aduerſary the diuell to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with but a more neere and dangerous enemy, and withall very ſubtill, euen our owne fleſh, which is ready vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery occaſion to betray vs into the hands of Sathan, &amp; haue we not then good reaſon alwayes to walke in feare? If we had in our houſes a theeviſh ſeruant, albeit he did not lay waite for our liues, nor were any way likely to endanger our whole eſtate, but onely to defraud vs of ſome part of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, vvould wee not haue an eye to ſuch an one, and that continually? But eſpecially if we had one within our doores, that ſought all opportunities to deliuer vs into the hands of our mortall enemy, would wee not be euermore watchfull for the preuenting of ſuch a miſchiefe? How much more vigilant then ſhould wee be in matters ſpirituall, ſeeing that our naturall corruption is exceeding treacherous, and ready
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8504:10"/>vpon euery occaſion, not to procure vs ſome ſlight incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience, or ſmall loſſe, but to bring vs vnder the power and dominion of the Prince of darkeneſſe, vvho is a vowed aduerſary vnto all Gods elect.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly in regard of the Lord wee had need to keepe a perpetuall watch ouer our hearts:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for vvho knoweth how ſeuerely he may proceede againſt vs, if vve for neuer ſo little a while doe wilfully ſhake off the yoake of obedience? May not hee iuſtly giue vs ouer to a deluded minde, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane ſpirit, if we beginne to alow our ſoules in any knowen euill?</p>
                  <p>If vvee careleſſely reiect his holy lawes, may not his ſpirit iuſtly forſake our ſoule? If wee conclude thus in our owne thoughts, now will I take liberty for vvantonneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe; for oppreſſion and hard dealing, and ſuch like ſinnes, and hereafter I vvill become more chaſt and more mercifull, &amp;c. May not God euen at this time deliuerws vp as priſoners vnto Sathan (as hee hath dealt vvith ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) and cauſe him ſo to manacle our hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that it ſhall coſt vs many a bitter teare, ere wee recouer our former libertie and freedome of ſpirit? Nay further, how if God ſhould take vs with the manner, and at that time ſtrip vs of life it ſelfe? Surely albeit, wee being the ſeruants of the Lord and dying in repentance cannot periſh vtterly, yet ſhall we depart hence very vncomfortably, and not leaue ſo good a report behinde vs, as otherwiſe vve might haue done.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine thus confirmed, ſerueth,</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> for the ſharpe reproofe of ſuch aspropoſe vnto themſelues ſet times, vvherein they will giue their fleſh the ſwing, and let looſe the raines vnto too much licenciouſneſſe. And as at other times, ſo eſpecially vpon the Lords day, when God would haue them wholy to attend vpon him, then they take liberty for their vile and ſinfull luſts: giuing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ouer either to idleneſſe at home or (which is worſe) vnto profaneneſſe abroad. For the weeke dayes, many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues ordinarily vvithin ſome good compaſſe,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8504:11"/>being imployed in the workes of their vocation, but on the Sabbath, which the Lord hath ſet apart as holy vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, they runne violently vnto all manner of ſinnefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, and baſe exerciſes and ſports; and ſo of Gods day they make that the Diuels day: in ſo much that hee then knowes whereabout hee ſhall finde them, euen buſily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in his worke; for they at ſundry ſeaſons openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, (and that a twelue moneths before) Ryot, and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Carding, and Dicing, and dalliance, and ſuch like horrible abuſes, and make it knowne that then they minde to keepe open houſe for ſinne and Sathan, when they ſhould ſet open the gates of their harts that the King of glory might enter in, and dwell there by his holy Word and bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Theſe are farre from that conſtant watchfulneſſe and holy feare of falling, which this Text requireth, and euen as farre from hauing any part and portion in that reſt, which heere is promiſed vnto all that faithfully labour to attaine thereunto.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> let this be for our inſtruction, that we be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer remiſſe, and negligent, what workes ſoeuer we be about, and what company ſoeuer we conuerſe withall. When wee eate and drinke, let vs doe it with feare (as <hi>Iude</hi> requireth) leaſt our owne Table become a ſnare vnto vs, and we be too much carried away with a carnall delight in the creatures. When we are exerciſed in the workes of our callings, let vs heedfully looke vnto our affections, leaſt we be too farre led aſide after the world, and leaſt we ſerue our owne turnes, rather then ſeeke Gods glory in that which wee doe. Yea, when we are buſied in the exerciſes of Religion, let vs take heed that our hearts be vpright with God therein, and that we be not groſly tainted and corrupted with hypocriſie, and pride, and vaineglory; which are ready to intermixe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with our beſt actions,</p>
                  <p>And ſo for our company, albeit it be ſo good and ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that wee ſee no likelyhood of infection ſo long as wee conuerſe with ſuch, yet let vs not be ſecure; no, not when we aſſociate our ſelues with the beſt that are, fo if we he, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8504:11"/>they may hurt vs, or we them, by ſpeech, or example, one way or other: and if it ſtand vs vpon to be iealous of our ſelues when we haue to doe with thoſe that are moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, much more ought we to walke in feare when we are compelled vpon any occaſion to deale with prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are euer and anon caſting forth lewd, and wanton, and wicked ſpeeches, and ſeeking to corrupt men with vile and diuelliſh opinions.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> here is matter of conſolation for them that are thus conſtantly watchfull, and doe at no time forſake the promiſe of entring into Gods reſt, by turning out of thoſe pathes, which he hath preſcribed them to walke in: they are in a ſafe and happy eſtate, whatſoeuer changes &amp; alterations fall out in the world: though Satan rage, and his inſtruments grow boyſterous, and hypocrites fall away on euery ſide, yet ſhall they ſtand faſt and firme, and not ſo much as ſeeme to be depriued of that reſt which the Lord hath prouided for them; neither is this a thing impoſſible, as ſome do ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, but that which many of the Saints haue attained vnto, who haue conſtantly walked before the Lord in their vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, and neuer all their life time after their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion broken forth into any hainous and preſumptuous euill, as may be ſeene in <hi>Abraham, Moſes, Iob, Paul,</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> by name, who is ſayd to haue walked with God, euen in that ſinnefull generation wherein he liued. And if wee ſtriue to attaine vnto this, aſſuredly wee ſhall haue the Lords aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and be inabled at all times and in all things to keepe a good conſcience both before God and men.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>[Forſaking the promiſe of entring into his reſt, &amp;c.]</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> Hence we may note this Doctrine, that,
<note place="margin">Without Faith the promiſes are of no force,</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The hearing of the promiſes is not ſufficient for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of ſaluation, vnleſſe by faith we lay hold on the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe Iſraelites of whom mention is made in this Text had the glad tidings of the Goſpell preached vnto them, but the word that they heard profited them not, becauſe it was not mixed with faith in thoſe that heard, Chap. 4 2. Thoſe impious and blaſphemous Iewes, which railed vpon <hi>Paul</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8504:12"/>his Doctrine, and contraried the things which were ſpoken by him,
<note place="margin">Act. 13.38.</note> had the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes through Chriſt preached and proffered vnto them, and yet had no benefite thereby. <hi>Iudas</hi> himſelfe was preſent among the hearers of our Sauiour, when he made that heauenly Sermon (<hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. and 7. wherein are contained many bleſſed promiſes; yet was he neuer the better for that, but rather much worſe, becauſe hee gaue not intertainement thereunto: his ſinne was thereby increaſed; and ſo is theirs, whoſoeuer they be, that make no better vſe of the promiſes than he did. <hi>If I had not come and ſpoken vnto them</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>they had had no ſinne;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 15.22.</note> to wit, in compariſon, they had beene nothing ſo faultie as they were; when he had preached the Goſpell vnto them, and they had reiected the ſame, that did exceedingly aggrauate their ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Here then are thoſe to be reproued that are ready when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer any occaſion is offered to diſcourſe at large of the bleſſedneſſe of theſe times wherein wee liue,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> aboue thoſe wherein our forefathers liued. For then (ſay they) there was nothing but palpable ignorance: the Scriptures were hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from the common ſort; being in a tongue that they could not vnderſtand, neither might they without perill of their liues ſearch into the ſame. But now the caſe is farre different: wee haue libertie to heare the inſtructions of the Word in publike, and to reade the ſame in priuate, and thus farre they ſay well: but what vſe doe they make of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell that is offered vnto them? doe not they, for all their good words, eyther abſent themſelues from the preaching of it, or if they repaire vnto it, is it not for faſhion rather than for conſcience? Doe they not come to carpe eyther at the matter, or at the manner of deliuery, rather than to be edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thereby? If their conſciences teſtifie againſt them that they are guilty in theſe things, they haue ſmall cauſe to glory of the happineſſe of our times. For albeit the light of the Goſpell doe tend to the ſaluation of many, yet it ſhall be for the increaſe of condemnation vnto them who doe not receiue the promiſes thereof, nor obey the precepts that are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8504:12"/>deliuered vnto them: both which doe alwayes goe together; for whoſoeuer refuſeth to walke in the wayes of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, hee doeth withall reiect the promiſes; and therfore though the Land be happy in regard of the Word, yet hee is miſerable, becauſe he reapeth no benefit thereby.</p>
                  <p>Now that we may more carefully eſchew this ſinne, let vs conſider how the promiſe of entring into that holy reſt is forſaken, and that is done ſundry wayes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by too much preſumption,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> when men ſtand vpon the goodnes of their nature,
<note place="margin">Hovv the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Rom. 10.3.</note> vpon their owne innocencie and worthineſſe, and ſo thinke the promiſe needles, as the Apoſte witneſſeth that the Iewes did, who going about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſnes, did not ſubmit themſelues vnto the righteouſnes of faith: and likewiſe ſo doe all that are abſolute Papiſts, and thinke to merit by their owne workes. Of this ſort alſo are all ignorant perſons, who profeſſe that they doe not expect any great comfort by hearing of Sermons; they hope they haue liued long enough to know how to be ſaued: and as for ſeruing of God, they haue had a good deuotion euer ſince they were borne, and they truſt they haue as good hearts to God-ward, and as good a beleefe in him as the beſt of them all, that can talke ſo much of the Scriptures. Alas poore ſilly people, their caſe is lamentable, whatſoeuer they imagine: for all the while they intertaine ſo good a conceit of themſelues, they cannot poſſibly flie vnto God for mercy in Chriſt Ieſus,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2.</note> but are ſtrangers from the couenants of promiſe; and howſoeuer they brag of their hope of eternall life, yet (as the Apoſtle ſayth) they are without hope, and without God in the world: and therefore if euer they looke to be cured by the great Phyſition of our ſoules, Chriſt Ieſus, let them labour to ſee their ſpirituall maladies; for he came not to heale thoſe that thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues whole, but ſuch alone as feele themſelues to be ſicke, and doe eſteeme it a ſingular benefit to haue a through cure wrought vpon their ſoules.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the promiſe is forſaken through infidelity,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> when men thinke it to be booteleſſe for them to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8504:13"/>the ſame, and that there is not therein vertue ſufficient to bring them vnto heauen: whence it comes to paſſe that if they be ſet vpon by feares and terrors, they ſinke vnder the ſame, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did, notwithſtanding all the ſweet promiſes which hee hard from his Maiſter. And as for their ſoules, ſo for their eſtate, if they be poore and behinde hand, or any other way diſtreſſed, they imagine it to be a folly for them to caſt their care vpon God, and to reſt vpon his promiſe, who hath ſaid that hee vvill not faile, nor forſake thoſe that depend vpon him: they will neuer put him to it, nor try what he will doe for them (as wicked <hi>Ahaz</hi> profeſſed when hee was in danger of the enemy. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.12.) but they will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhift for themſelues, and vſe falſhood and lying, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ill meanes they can deuiſe for the releiuing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, this alſo is to reiect the promiſe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they alſo are guilty of the ſame crime, that doe preferre earthly things before heauenly.
<note place="margin">Luk. 14.26.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee that doth not forſake father and mother, wife and children, lands and goods,</hi> and all that he hath or might haue, <hi>for Chriſt his ſake, and the Gospels,
<note place="margin">Luk. 14.24.</note> is not worthy of him.</hi> And therefore were they reiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as vnmeete gueſts for the heauenly banquet, who made more account of their farmes, their oxen, and ſuch like out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard things, than they did of thoſe ſpirituall comforts which the Lord offered vnto them: And in like ſort ſhall they be iudged and condemned as contemners of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of life, who doe more greedily ſeeke after gold, and ſiluer, and periſhable ſubſtance, than they doe after the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of a better life, which are permanent and euerlaſting. Indeede Gods people are oftentimes ouercaried with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate affection towards the things of this world, and luſt breaketh in vpon them, but they giue no harbour nor lodging therevnto in their hearts, neither doe they loue theſe lying vanities, more than grace and godlineſſe, but would willingly giue the Maiſter a place aboue the ſeruants, though they, as rude and vnmannerly gueſts, doe ſtriue for the chiefe roome in their ſoules: they would gladly preferre the glory of God and the meanes of their ſaluation before
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8504:13"/>all the kingdomes of the earth, &amp; deſire theſe outward things onely as helpes and furtherances thereunto. And thus wee ſee how the promiſes may be reiected.</p>
                  <p>Now a ſecond vſe of this point ſhalbe for our inſtruction,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> that ſeeing the hearing of the promiſes is not ſufficient for the procuring of our eternall happineſſe, but the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and applying of the ſame is alſo required of vs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ſhould with all earneſtneſſe take hold thereof, and by faith make them our owne: preferring them before all that this world can afford vs, and being content to relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh whatſoeuer wee poſſeſſe for the purchaſing of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pearle. And when once we haue obtained it,
<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> let vs hide the ſame within our hearts, and keepe it as our very life, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer making ſhipwracke of a good conſcience, leaſt thereby our ſaith and comfort in the promiſes be much weakened and diminiſhed, but holding on a conſtant courſe in the wayes of pietie, that ſo our inward ioy and aſſurance of Gods fauour may be ſtill continued and dayly increaſed. And for the ſame end, let vs be often meditating, and conferring of the promiſes, and be willing to hearken vnto others that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in publike or in priuate doe their beſt endeuour to adde further ſtrength vnto our faith. Thus if vvee can doe, wee ſhalbe ſure of a portion in the heauenly promiſes, vvhen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhalbe puniſhed for refuſing of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of entring into his rest.]</hi> That is into eternall bleſſedneſſe in the heauens, and the aſſurance of enioying the ſame here vpon the earth: according to that in the 3. <hi>Verſe, Wee that beleeue are entring into reſt.</hi> Whence wee may learne this doctrine, that,</p>
                  <p>The ſtate of Chriſtianity is a ſtate of reſt.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label> 
                  </p>
                  <p>The land of Canaan,
<note place="margin">Chriſtianity is a ſtate of reſt.</note> whereinto the children of Iſrael en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred after their long and tedious trauell in the wildernſſe, was a tipe thereof, and therefore is it called Gods reſt; but he doth not ſo greatly ſtand vpon that, becauſe reprobates were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into it as well as his choſen people: but he putteth vs in minde of a better reſt, euen the ſtate of grace and of glory, which his elect, and they alone, ſhall haue the fruition of.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:8504:14"/>
                  <p>our Sauiour confirmeth this point vnto vs, where he ſayth, <hi>Come vnto me all yee that are wearie and laden,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.28.</note> and I will eaſe you. Take my yoake on you, &amp;c. and you ſhall finde rest vnto your ſoules.</hi> Heere wee ſee what an happy caſe they are in that betake themſelues vnto Chriſt for reliefe and comfort, ſubmitting themſelues vnto his holy gouernment, though they haue maniſold troubles and aduerſities without, yet they haue quietneſſe within, ſo long and ſo farre as they can diſburden their ſoules of all their ſorrowes and cares by caſting them vpon Chriſt Ieſus, as hee would haue them: all that while they are euen like men that inhabite in a ſtrong and inuincible Caſtle, who in the middes of bluſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtormes and windes that are round about them, and of violent aduerſaries that doe lay continuall ſeige againſt them, are merry and cheerefull, and fall to their foode, and betake them to their reſt, without any feare and diſtraction at all, as knowing that they are ſafe and ſure how ſoeuer they be aſſayled and oppoſed againſt: ſuch is the caſe of all godly men, what outward trials ſoeuer they haue, their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are at quiet within, as being confidently aſſured that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can befall them for their hurt: for indeed euery ſanctified Chriſtian is as ſafe from all miſchiefe as the very Angels of God in Heauen. Another proofe of this point wee haue in the Propheſie of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> where the Lord ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus, <hi>Stand in the wayes, and behold, and atke for the olde way,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 6.16.</note> which is the good way, and walke therein:</hi> and what then? <hi>ye ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that wee may yet more fully ſee into the truth of this doctrine, that grace, and peace, true godlineſſe, and ſound tranquilitie and quietneſſe doe euer accompany one another; let vs weigh theſe reaſons following.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> whoſoeuer is truely gracious, is deliuered from the troubleſome carriage of an ill conſcience; whereupon muſt needes enſue marueilous great eaſe: for ſinnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repented and vnpardoned, doe lye wonderfull heauie, and are vnto the ſoule euen as an ouerweighty burden is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8504:14"/>vnto a Ship, which is ready euer and anon to ſinke it, and to cauſe it to be ouerwhelmed and ſwallowed vp of the Waters: this burden CHRIST IESVS, doeth remoue as ſoone as euer hee beginneth to dwell in the heart by his holy Spirit, freeing vs from the terrour of a guiltie conſcience, and from the accuſations, and clamour, and continuall complaints of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as the guilt of ſinne is quite taken away,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſo is the power thereof greatly weakened by him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon much peace and quietneſſe muſt neceſſarily follow. For that partie is in great ſlauerie and bondage that liues vnder the dominion of ſinne, being alwayes toſſed and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyled with one vnruly luſt or other, which makes him euermore vnquiet and reſtleſſe, as the raging waues of the Sea; or if at any time hee haue a little caſe, his torment is afterwards redoubled: now from this raigning power of iniquitie, all godly men are exempted, according to that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who, ſpeaking of regenerate men, ſaith, that <hi>the olde man is crucified in them,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.6.</note> that the body of ſinne might be deſtroyed, that hencefoorth they ſhould not ſerue ſinne:</hi> to which purpoſe he alſo addeth, <hi>Sinne ſhall not haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer you, verſ.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, whoſoeuer is indued with ſauing grace,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is freed from many doubts and feares concerning his eſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch perils as may befall his body: for as touching the charge and care of prouiſion, and protection, the Lord himſelfe vndertakes it for him, ſo that hee may and muſt quietly and cheerefully labour in his calling, and neuer trouble himſelfe with the ſucceſſe, but leaue that vnto God, who hath promiſed to care for thoſe that caſt their care vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and to be a defence vnto thoſe, that commit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto him. It muſt needs be very burdenſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mightieſt man that is (although hee haue many thouſands comming in by the yeere) to take vpon him the maintenance of himſelfe, and of thoſe that doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon him: for hee cannot but be many times mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull of his eſtate, in regard of many caſualties
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8504:15"/>which he is ſubiect vnto, and ſo be perplexed and diſtracted with feare, that he ſhall not be able to maintaine his port, and to vphold his dignitie in ſuch ſort as he deſireth: and what a quieting then muſt it of neceſſitie be vnto the heart of a man, to haue this burden taken off his ſhoulders, vnder which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe walke ſo heauily, and to be freed from a number of carking and vexing thoughts, by relying on Gods gracious prouidence for all the meanes of this temporall life?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly and laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> grace freeth ſuch as haue it from the feare of death and of hell, which cauſeth thoſe that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the guilt and power of ſinne to be in marueilous great bondage all their life long, as the writer of this Epiſtle wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. For albeit vnregenerate men put away from them the thoughts of death as much as poſſibly they can, yet when any grieuous ſickeneſſe is vpon them or any the like meſſenger of death approcheth vnto them, and doth as it were, knocke at their dores, they are commonly very much diſquieted, and in very ſore diſtreſſe and anguiſh; but as euery one is more religious, ſo his deſolution and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence is leſſe terrible vnto him, nay, vſually, no newes can be more welcome vnto ſuch than that they muſt ſhortly leaue this ſinnefull and wretched world; for then they know they ſhall make an happy change, and inſtead of the Earth enioy Heauen: <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours:
<note place="margin">Reuel. 14.13. Iſa. 57.2. Pſal. 16.</note> their bodies reſt in the graue as in their beds; and their ſoules goe to the full fruition of that reſt, which was but begunne heere vpon the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which ſerueth in the firſt place for the confutation of their errour which iudge a Chriſtian life to be of all other the moſt tedious and troubleſome,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> fulleſt of feare and of vexations; which imagine that the profeſſours of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell are perpetually as it were vpon a racke, in ſo much that for their owne parts they would more willingly ſit all day in the ſtockes than be at religious exerciſes; and chuſe rather to liue in <hi>Bridewell,</hi> than in thoſe places where they ſhall be tyed to the outward performance of Chriſtian duties. But what ſayth the Lord concerning this matter? doth not hee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8504:15"/>auouch that the ſtate of a Chriſtian is a ſtate of reſt, and of peace? and which ſhall we giue credite vnto, eyther the wiſe God or fooliſh men?</p>
                  <p>But (ſome will ſay) how can it be that their eſtate ſhould be ſo full of quietneſſe,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                     </label> ſeeing that they are continually ſubiect to afflictions, and perſecutions, &amp; temptations as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelues, beſides daily experience do euidently ſhew.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe doe not at all breake off their quietneſſe ſo long as they keepe their peace with God;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> for they are but as it were ſtormes and boyſterous windes that beate at the windowes and vpon the outſide of the houſe, ſo that their inward man, <hi>to wit,</hi> their minds and conſciences, are nothing diſquieted thereby; or if they be, it proceedeth not from the hauing of grace, but from the want thereof, and as they grow more religious, ſo their hearts are ſtill more calme and quiet.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, heere is matter as of incouragement,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> to cauſe men to enter into the courſe of chriſtianitie, (becauſe how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be a warfare, yet it is not a dangerous, but a ſafe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare) ſo alſo of ſingular conſolation vnto thoſe that haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made entrance into the ſame. For, whereas all men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to liue at hearts eaſe, they doe indeed take the ready way thereunto, for it hath bene before ſufficiently confirmed, that religion bringeth men vnto reſt and quietneſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let them expect it, and pray for it, and they ſhall be ſure not to miſſe of it.</p>
                  <p>Now, becauſe our reſt and peace is eyther more or leſſe, according to the meaſure of our holineſſe: and our ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in this life is but in part, and therefore our reſt alſo imperfect: this ſhould make vs long for the day of our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification, when wee ſhall be indued with perfect holineſſe, and ſo attaine to perfect reſt: in this world wee enioy a great deale more than any naturall man can conceiue, but in the life to come wee ſhall enioy infinitely more than wee our ſelues can now conceiue: which ſhould cauſe vs with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to paſſe through the troubleſome and tempeſtuous Sea of this world, in hope that we ſhall ſhortly arriue at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8504:16"/>Hauen of reſt where wee long to be,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.6.8.10.</note> 
                     <hi>for it is a iuſt thing with God to giue rest vnto them that are troubled. When the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſhall ſhew himſelfe from Heauen with his mighty Angels, to be glorified in his Saints, and to be made maruailous in all them that beleeue in that day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Any of you,]</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>7</label> Whence obſerue this Doctrine, that.</p>
                  <p>The care of ſaluation belongeth to euery one indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently.
<note place="margin">Religious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties pertaine vnto all.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hee that would not be damned and eternally deſtroyed, muſt be heedfull and watchfull ouer his wayes, of what ſtate, condition, or age ſoeuer he be, there is no diſpenſation for any; Magiſtrate and Subiect, Miniſter and People, Maſter and Seruant, Men and Women, yong and old, are all bound to be carefull for the happy eſtate of their ſoules: God in this regard, is no reſpecter of perſons, but requireth this care of euery one as well as of any one.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is that the Scripture giues ſuch generall exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations vnto pietie,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 49.1. <hi>Heare this all yee people, giue eare all ye that dwell in the world, aſwell low as high, both rich and poore.</hi> And againe in the Goſpell according to <hi>Marke,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 13.37.</note> our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Thoſe things that I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto all men:</hi> Watch.</p>
                  <p>And further, the LORD in denouncing and executing his iudgements maketh no diſtinction of perſons, but threatneth and inflicteth his plagues vpon all ſorts, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their works: and as they haue beene greater offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſo doe they meete with ſorer puniſhments: the Lord ſpareth none, as we may note in the Reuelation, where is ſhewed, that when God came to manifeſt the fierceneſſe of his wrath againſt rebellious ſinners, <hi>The Kings of the Earth, and the great men,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.15.16.</note> and the rich men, and the chiefe Captaines, and the mightie men, and euery bondman, and euery free-man hid themſelues in dens, and among the Rocks of the Mountaines. And ſayd to the Mountaines and Rocks; Fall on vs, and hide vs from the preſence of him that ſitteth vpon the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe.</hi> In which place we ſee that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the great command of Potentates, nor the fortitude of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8504:16"/>Warrtours, nor the riches of the wealthie, nor the baſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the meaner ſort, can ſtand them in any ſtead. when the Lord entreth into iudgement with them; but all that haue in them raging ſinnes ſhall be tormented with helliſh feares.</p>
                  <p>Againe Gods mercies and graces and the teſtimonies of his fauour are offered vnto all ſorts,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſo that none needs to complaine that his ſeruing of the Lord vvill be bootleſſe: though the gates of great men be opened vnto ſome and ſhut againſt others, it is not ſo with heauen-gate: that ſtands wide open vnto all, that through the faithfull and conſcion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vſe of the meanes, doe ſtriue to enter in.
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.28.</note> 
                     <hi>For in Chriſt Ieſus there is neither Iew, nor Graecian, Barbarian, nor Scithian, bond nor free, male nor female,</hi> but in him, <hi>all are one:</hi> that is, all are equally reſpected without any perſonall difference; for God regardeth not one country more than another; one nation more than another: the Maiſter hath no prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence aboue the ſeruant, vnleſſe he be more religious; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall the ſeruant haue a leſſe reward than the Maiſter, except hee be leſſe gracious: women are accepted with the Lord as well as men, neither hath hee any regard of the one ſexe more than of the other. Seeing then that he impoſeth on all men, without exception an holy care of their ſaluation, and puniſheth all thoſe that neglect it, and rewardeth all ſuch as obſerue it, the vſe hereof is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 For the confutation of their errour who imagine that this is not a thing pertayning vnto all,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> but properly belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto Miniſters, and vnto thoſe that are learned, and haue time and leaſure for ſuch buſineſſes: but as for others, vvhat ſhould they meddle vvith matters of Religion: at leaſt in any ſerious manner? Indeed they would haue ſome kinde of men to be able to ſay ſomewhat in points of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, that ſo they might, if occaſion be offered, ſhew their good education, their vvit, their elocution and ſuch like good parts of nature: but for tradeſmen, huſbandmen, poore ſeruants, and eſpecially for women, to be exerciſed in the ſcriptures and matters of Godlineſſe, they thinke it an abſurde and vnreaſonable thing. But what? Haue not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8504:17"/>they ſoules as vvell as others? And haue not they ſinne, in their ſoules that needes purging as well as others? And can ſinne be purged away by any other meanes than by thoſe vvhich God hath ordayned? And if it be not waſhed away can there any vncleane thing enter into the kingdome of heauen? If not, what vnmercifulneſſe is it in them to deny vnto any the carefull and conſcionable vſe of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, whereby they ſhould be made vncapeable of that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall happineſſe? Away therefore with this hatefull and dangerous errour, that ſome are exempted from that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vvatchfulneſſe and care of the duties of piety and of righteouſneſſe, vvhich is enioyned vnto others: neither let vs ſuffer our mindes and our hearts to be corrupted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but vvhether wee be men or women, young or old, poore or rich, baſe or honourable, let vs take vpon vs this burden vvhich the Lord vvould haue all to beare, euen to ſtand in continuall feare of prouoking his Maieſty, either by ruſhing vpon thoſe euils which he hath forbidden, or by omitting thoſe duties which he hath commanded.</p>
                  <p>And, to preſſe this point a little further, let not great men be deluded vvith this conceit, that they ſtand not in need of prayer, and of the vvord in publike and in priuate; that they are not bound to mourne for their faults, to ſeeke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation vvith God, to deſire the admonitions of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and the like; let not great men (I ſay) deceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vvith ſuch vaine imaginations: for if any ought to be more carefull of Gods ſeruices than other, ſurely they are the men: for they receiue moſt vvages and therefore muſt they doe moſt worke: they haue the ſtrongeſt enemies, and therefore need moſt heedfully to ſtand vpon their guard: they meet vvith the moſt dangerous ſnares, and therefore muſt be moſt wary of their ſteps, leaſt at any time they be entangled. Yet ſo farre hath Sathan bewitched a great number, that they thinke it a derogation to their dignitie to ſuffer the words of exhortation or of admonition; to be put in minde of offences committed, or of duties omitted, thoſe things (they thinke) pertaine to men of inferiour note:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8504:17"/>they vvould ſeeme to cary away all the preferment, and yet when the queſtion is concerning the chiefe preferment of all, which is to be a found Chriſtian, they put euery body before themſelues: they are content that others ſhall be Kings, but they will be vaſſalls vnto ſinne and Sathan. What folly, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther madneſſe is this? Doe they imagine that they ſhall not come to iudgement as well as others? Doth not experience manifeſt vnto them, that age creepeth vpon them, as well as vpon others? That ſickneſſe taketh hold of them as well as of others? That horrible vexations and terrours doe ſeaſe on them, as vvell as on others? And why then doth it not enter into their hearts, that damnation belongs vnto them as well as vnto others, if by ſpeedy repentance they doe not preuent the ſame?</p>
                  <p>Now as ſome doe fondly and falſly conceiue that they ſhall be boren vvith in regard of their greatneſſe, ſo doe others hope in regard of their meaneneſſe to be diſpenſed with. We are poore day-labourers, and ſeruants (ſay they) who are to be imployed in worldly affaires, and to ſpend our whole time that way: I hope it is not required of vs that wee ſhould be skild in the ſcriptures, be able to conceiue prayer, able to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh offenders, &amp;c. And therefore either they abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the Church altogether, or els are careleſſe and negligent, and ſleepie when they are there: and if they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to an account, and examined vvhat they remember, they make anſwere, that they are wearied out with labouring in the weeke dayes, and therefore they muſt haue reſt vpon the Sabbath day: That they were hired for their worke, and that they will doe and no more: they will not be examined, nor catechized, nor be held to any ſuch ſtrict orders. But doth not the Lord in his holy word require obedience of poore men, and of ſeruants, as farre forth as of any? Doth not he in the fourth commandement enioyne them to obſerue, not a bodily reſt alone (as beaſts doe) but an holy reſt? And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, they ſay that they are ſo toyled out with worke that they cannot liſten to Gods word, that is but a fleſhly and diuelliſh excuſe: for vvhen the Sermon is ended, they are freſh and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8504:18"/>liuely enough to follow after their ſports and ſinnefull recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, if they may haue libertie ſo to doe, and can take more paines that way than they haue done in their callings all the weeke before; and therefore theſe vaine ſhifts ſhall not ſerue their turnes: Gods threatnings are denounced againſt them, and his iudgements haue beene executed vpon ſuch, as they are heeretofore, and ſo ſhall they be ſtill; profane ſeruants and ſinnefull poore men were not ſpared in the deſtruction of the olde world, and of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorra:</hi> and wee reade in the Goſpell, that at the comming of Chriſt thoſe that are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the Field,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.40.41.</note> and women that are grinding at the Mill, ſhall be ſome of them caſt off vnto deſtruction, as well as others are receiued vnto ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>But all ſeruants are not of ſo meane a condition as ſome, but there are a ſecond ſort, that haue another pretence for their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting off of Chriſt his yoake, and they are ſuch as are followers of great men; who alledge, that it is not for their Maſters ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for them to be religious, or (as they tearme it) preciſe; but to be proud and quarrelſome: to be ruffians and roiſters: to be ſwearers and blaſphemers: to be drunkards, and whore-Maiſters: theſe, they thinke, be for the credite of the houſe vnto which they appertaine, and by theſe practiſes they hope to be-pleaſe their Maſters. But when they haue ſpent their daies in theſe courſes, can their Maſters ſaue them from perdition, which by their leudneſſe they haue iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued? no ſurely, the holy Ghoſt ſpeaking of the mighty ones of the world ſayth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.7.8.</note> that <hi>they cannot redeeme their brother, nor giue his ranſome to God:</hi> they cannot procure their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life to be prolonged one day, nay nor one moment, much leſſe can they purchaſe the redemption of their ſoules, that they ſhould liue for euer, and that in perpetuall bliſſe and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Others there are that thinke they may haue a tolleration to be vaine and ſinnefull, becauſe they are yong; eſpecially, if they haue this reſolution, that when their youthfull bloud is ſpent, and the vigour of their bodies gone, they will betake themſelues to more ſober courſes, and repent for that which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8504:18"/>is paſt; but till that time if they take their libertie vpon the Lords day, and liue in idleneſſe and profaneneſſe euery day, you muſt pardon them: but will God pardon them? doth not he ſay, <hi>Remember thy creatour in the dayes of thy youth,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1.</note> whiles the euill dayes come not, nor the yeeres approach, wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them.</hi> And if they will not take his aduiſe, marke what he ſayth in another place, <hi>Reioyce,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.9.</note> O yong man, in thy youth, and let thine heart cheare thee in the dayes of thy youth, &amp;c.</hi> This they can well like of, &amp; be too rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to put in practiſe: but what followeth? <hi>But know</hi> (ſayth the Lord) <hi>that for all theſe things thou muſt be brought to iudgement. Dauid</hi> found that the ſinnes of his youth lay heauy vpon him, and therefore prayeth <hi>God would not remember them:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.7.</note> and ſhall we make ſo light of them? <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſheth <hi>Timothy,</hi> a very ſanctified and mortified yong man, <hi>to flie the luſts of youth;</hi> and ſhall we let looſe the raines thereunto, as if they were matters of nothing? ah; let vs not be ſo foole-hardie vnto our owne ruine and ouerthrow: but conſidering how fearfully the Lord doth iudge many young men that giue vp themſelues to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and adulterie, and theft, and all manner of vile and ſinfull behauiour, as namely, that ſome of them die an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death, being either brought to the gallowes, or ſome other way ſtrangely cut off: and that others hauing great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes left vnto them, are notwithſtanding caſt into extreme miſerie and neceſſitie: and that ſome others being well deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, are for all that branded with egregious infamie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch: conſidering (I ſay) theſe and the like extraordinary to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods heauie diſpleaſure againſt ſundrie liſencious yong men; let vs take warning by their example, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate the firſt fruits of our yeeres vnto him, by ſpending our time religiouſlie and profitablie in ſome good courſe or other.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> ſithence the care of ſaluation pertaineth vnto all indifferently: let Miniſters hence learne to deale equally with thoſe that are vnder their charge and not know any man after the fleſh, to reſpect him more or leſſe for that hee is rich, or poore, high or low, or the like; but giue euery one their due
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8504:19"/>portion of ſpirituall food, which they in the wiſedome of the Spirit iudge to be moſt fit for them: let them not feare to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter an admonition or reprehenſion to the greateſt and wealthieſt: neither let them neglect to giue an exhortation, or conſolation to the pooreſt and meaneſt, when neede doth require. But herein many doe lamentably offend, who if ſome great one of their charge be preſent, will afford them a Sermon, but if they be abſent, the reſt ſhall goe without. This is wretched partialitie; nay, indeed groſſe carnalitie and folly, and argueth that they are men-pleaſers, and ſeeke themſelues in their doctrine, and not Chriſt Ieſus; in that they haue moſt regard of thoſe that are commonly the moſt vnprofitable hearers, and neglect ſuch as vſually reape moſt fruit by preaching: for (ordinarily) <hi>the poore receiue the Goſpell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Seeme to be depriued.]</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>8</label> Whence ariſeth this point, that,</p>
                  <p>The Lord would not onely haue men to be in the ſtate of ſaluation,
<note place="margin">There muſt be no appearance of being out of the ſtate of Grace. 2 Cor. 13.6.</note> but would haue it knowen that they are in that ſtate, that there might be no ſuſpition of the contrary.</p>
                  <p>Therefore is it, that the Apoſtle ſaith vnto the <hi>Corinthians, I truſt that ye ſhall know that we are not reprobates.</hi> Where the word <hi>[I truſt]</hi> implyeth not any doubtfulneſſe, but indeed a certaintie of the thing affirmed. And this had <hi>Demetrius</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vnto,
<note place="margin">3 Iob ver. 12.</note> of whom the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius hath a good report of all men, and of the truth it ſelfe: yea, and we our ſelues beare record, and ye know that our record is true.</hi> He carried himſelfe ſo holily that he had a good teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie from all Gods people, from the truth which hee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, and practiſed, and from the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe, who doeth in a ſort miniſterially commend him: ſo that, looke what he ſayd of him, the holy Ghoſt ſayd the ſame; in which regard hee addeth, <hi>and yee know that our record is true, and that we are not deceiued.</hi> Now, that it is neceſſary to make knowne our goodneſſe by a Chriſtian conuerſation, that both we our ſelues and other may haue a well grounded perſwaſion of our happy eſtate, may appeare by theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> becauſe that will be a marueilous great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto vs in the ſeruices of God, in that we are aſſured that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8504:19"/>whatſoeuer we doe ſhall be both accepted and rewarded of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> wee may then boldly reproue and admoniſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; neither need we be afrayd of that byting Prouerbe, <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition heale thy ſelfe:</hi> for all men may cleerely ſee, that we haue healed our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, this brings great honour with it,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſo that Chriſtians dare truſt vs, and lay open their hearts vnto vs: yea, wicked men will reuerence vs, and in their diſtreſſes ſeeke vnto vs for counſell and comfort, and ſometimes put vs in truſt with their wils, and for the diſpoſing of their goods, and of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after their death, rather than carnall friends that are in bandes of nature neerely linked vnto them.</p>
                  <p>This ſhould teach vs to giue all diligence (as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth) to make our calling and election ſure;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.</note> and that not onely vnto our owne ſoules, but as farre as poſſibly we can, to giue teſtimonie thereof vnto other mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. If euer wee will vſe diligence in any thing, let it be in this. It is good husbandry to make ſure for our outward eſtate, and not to builde vpon vaine hopes; much more is it a point of wiſedome carefully to looke vnto the ſtate of our ſoules, which ſhould be a thouſand times deerer vnto vs than our bodies. If we be doubtfull that there is ſome dangerous diſeaſe growing vpon vs that is likely to take away our life, who is there among vs, but will ſeeke vnto the Phyſition to preuent that miſchiefe? how much more carefull ſhould we be of our ſoules, when wee plainely perceiue that there is not onely a deadly ſickneſſe vpon them, but that they are already dead in ſinne, &amp; in danger to be damned eternally if we ſeeke not vnto Chriſt Ieſus for a ſpeedie remedy? Let vs not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and careleſſe in a matter of ſuch conſequence:
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.4.</note> but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for a working faith, and a diligent loue, that ſo not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we our ſelues, but others alſo that haue the ſpirit of diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, may know that we are the elect of God, by the fruits of godlineſſe, appearing in vs, and proceeding from vs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> here are thoſe to be reproued that are content to liue in perplexitie and anguiſh of heart, in regard of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8504:20"/>of their ſaluation, rather than they will be at the paines to haue this aſſurance ſealed vnto their ſoules. As alſo, thoſe that would faine haue a good opinion among men, and deſire much to be reputed heires of ſaluation, and yet ſhew forth ſo little pietie towards God, and loue towards their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that they cauſe their wiſeſt and beſt friends to be ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To be depriued.]</hi> The word that is vſed in the originall, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth properly to come too late, as ſuiters doe that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented; and alſo to be out-runne in a race, and ſo to loſe the prize: both which ſenſes may well ſtand, and from thence this Doctrine may be raiſed, that,</p>
                  <p>Many haue ſome likelihood of ſaluation,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>9</label>
                     <note place="margin">Many ſeeme to be religious, who yet miſſe of ſaluation.</note> and yet faile of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>For otherwiſe the holy Ghoſt would neuer haue gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſtirre them vp to an holy watchfulneſſe ouer their hearts and wayes, by this reaſon <hi>[Lest any ſhould ſeeme to bee depriued,]</hi> for if ſome did not come ſhort of ſaluation, that in appearance ſought for it, how ſhould any ſeeme to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? therefore it is plaine out of this text, that ſome may be in a ſort ſuiters for eternall life, and yet miſſe of it, and runne (though not as they ought to doe) the race of Chriſtianitie, and yet not obtaine the crowne, which is propoſed to thoſe, that with a faithfull and true heart doe ſeeke for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>This may be ſeene in the fooliſh Virgins,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> who made an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall profeſſion and ioyned with the wiſe Virgins in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, and thought to haue beene receiued with them, when the Bride-groome came: but for all this they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, when the reſt were admitted.</p>
                  <p>The like we may obſerue in the ſtony and thorny ground, who receiued the ſeed, and brought forth the one the blade, and the other the eare as well as the blade; and yet neither of them were good grounds: and therefore the one ſort ſhrunke when perſecution came, and the other were carried away with the commodities and delights of this preſent life. So in this Epiſtle to the Hebrewes it is euident,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 6.</note> that ſome are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the Word, and haue ſome taſte of good things;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8504:20"/>and yet being not ſound in iudgement, nor ſincere in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they afterwards fall away vnto their eternall perdition.</p>
                  <p>Which ſhould cauſe vs to ſhake off all ſecuritie,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> and neuer to ſtand at a ſtay, but to goe forward in the wayes of godlineſſe, working out our ſaluation in feare and trembling:
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> not being ſo preſumptuous as many are, who hauing had ſome illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in heauenly things, and ſome flaſhes of good motions in their hearts; preſently conclude that they are in the ſtate of grace, and can neuer fall away from the faith: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon take libertie vnto themſelues to walke in many inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate courſes, which tend much to the diſhonour of God and the diſcredit of the Goſpell: and let them be admoniſhed, and haue the iudgements of God denounced againſt their ſinnes, they ſet light thereby, and profeſſe, that they feare not the threatnings of the Word, as knowing that they cannot but be ſaued. Let vs beware of this careleſſe diſpoſition, and hearken rather vnto the aduice of the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> who biddeth vs <hi>ſerue the Lord in feare, and reioyce before him with trembling:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> for notwithſtanding their carnall confidence and boldneſſe; they may, nay they ſhall (except they take better wayes) bee vtterly diſappointed of their expectation: for no prophane perſon hath any communion with the holy God,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.</note> and vnleſſe they clenſe themſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh, and of the ſpirit, the promiſes of life belong not vnto them.</p>
                  <p>Would we then build our aſſurance vpon a firmer foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, then ſuch kind of perſons do?
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> then let vs rowſe vp our ſelues from that dead ſlumber of ſecuritie, and ſet ſtraight ſteps in the pathes of righteouſneſſe, and while we haue light, let vs conſcionably walke in the ſame; for we know not how ſoone it may be taken from vs.</p>
                  <p>It is recorded by the Euangeliſt <hi>Luke,</hi> that when our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our drew neere vnto Ieruſalem, he wept for it, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Luke 19.42.</note> 
                     <hi>O if thou haddest knowne, at the least, in this thy day, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe things which belong vnto thy peace! but now are they hidde from thine eyes.</hi> As if he had ſaid if thou haddeſt wiſely conſidered of the ſeaſon, when the Lord offered vnto thee fauour and mercie, and had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt made vſe of the ſame, thou mighteſt haue beene happie,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8504:21"/>notwithſtanding all their former rebellions; but now thou art miſerable, becauſe thou wantedſt wiſdome to diſcerne the opportunitie. We haue through the preaching of the Goſpell the ſame offer of mercie that the Iewes had; let vs not be ſlacke in taking holde thereof, nor harden our hearts while it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to day, but ſeeke the Lord while he may be found, and call vpon him while he is neere: and looke how watchfull and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruant men will be of the fitteſt opportunitie for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their ſuites (eſpecially in matters that neerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne them) vnto an earthly Prince; ſo and much more vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant let vs be in obſeruing the beſt and meeteſt ſeaſon for the ſeeking and obtaining of fauour from the Lord of Heauen and Earth.</p>
                  <p>And whereas many doe ſeeme to be faire for the crowne of glory,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> and yet miſſe of the ſame: <hi>Let vs ſo runne, that wee may obtaine;</hi> caſting off euery thing that preſſeth vs downe, and hindereth our making of ſpeed in this race; and preſſing hard vnto the marke that is ſet before vs, vntill we haue attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto that happineſſe which we labour and ſtriue for. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience telleth men that the things of this life cannot be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vvithout great induſtry: but for eternall ſaluation they imagine (ſo fooliſh are the common ſort) that it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned without any great adoe; nay, that it ſhall be as it were caſt vpon them, whether they ſeeke for it or not. But if any thing be hard to be come by, it is euerlaſting life: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour biddeth vs,
<note place="margin">Luk. 13. Math. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Striue to enter in at the ſtraite gate for many, I ſay vnto you, will ſeeke to enter in, and ſhall not be able.</hi> As nothing is more ſure than eternall bleſſedneſſe, if we in a right manner labour for it; ſo nothing is more impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be gotten, if we vſe not all diligence for the obtayning of it.</p>
                  <p>Let vs therefore put our ſelues to it with all our might, reſoluing to breake through all manner of impediments that we ſhall meete with all, and making full account that we ſhall meete with a great many: for firſt of all our owne carnall and ſinnefull reaſon will ſet vpon vs, and obiect very dangerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt all the points of faith and of mortification: then
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8504:21"/>the luſts of the fleſh will riſe vp againſt the good motions of the ſpirit, and ſeeke to quench, or corrupt them: ſo that our reaſon we ſhall finde to be very vnreaſonable, and our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to affect the things that are moſt vnlawfull. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more the diuell wilbe a ſore enemy vnto vs, in which regard the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We wreſtle not againſt fleſh and bloud,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.2.3.</note> againſt weake aduerſaries, ſuch as the mightieſt men are in compariſon of Satan, but againſt principalities, and powers, &amp;c. And what of that, <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>take vnto you the whole armour of God, that you may be able to reſiſt in the euill day, &amp;c.</hi> Which exhortation we ſhould the rather giue heede vnto, becauſe otherwiſe wee ſhall light vpon Satans ſnares in euery thing wee ſet our ſelues about: he hath traps for vs in our recreations, in our eating and drinking, in our calings, yea in the very exerciſes of religion which wee performe, ſo that if wee be not very wary and circumſpect, we ſhall certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be inſnared. Laſtly we haue the world to diſcourage vs from well doing, and eſpecially our carnall friends, who proue commonly the moſt deadly and dangerous foes: for they will be euer and anon thruſting diuelliſh obiections into our heads: why will you be more ſtrict than your neighbours? (will they ſay:) Are there not vviſe men that much diſlike your courſe, and doe you not ſee that others cary away wealth and credit and preferment from ſuch as you are? What? doe you meane therefore, by your preciſeneſſe, not onely to diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage your ſelfe, but to vndoe your wife and children, and ſo to diſcredit and greiue all your friends? theſe and a thouſand ſuchlike obſtacles and lets wee ſhall meete with, when once we enter into a Chriſtian courſe: and therefore it ſtandeth vs vpon to looke narrowly vnto our ſteps, and to craue ſtrength from heauen that we may breake through all hinderances and oppoſitions. <hi>That ſo being faithfull vnto the death, we may not be depriued of the heauenly reſt, but at length attaine vnto the crowne of life, which God the righteous iudge will be bestow vpon vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8504:22"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8504:22"/>
                  <p>TWO SERMONS.</p>
                  <p>Of Chriſtian Loue and Life: On <hi>Canticles</hi> 2. <hi>Verſe</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>PREACHED AT Tedbury in Gloceſter-ſhire, vpon Chriſts <hi>Aſcention</hi>-day laſt paſt. 1612.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Richard Webb.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2 Corinth. 11.2.</hi>
                     </bibl> I am ielous ouer you, with a Godly ielouſie: for I haue prepared you for one husband, to preſent you as a pure Virgin to Chriſt.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by THO. SNODHAM, for ROGER IACKSON, and are to be ſould at his ſhop neere to Fleetſtreet Conduit 1613.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8504:23"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8504:23"/>
                  <head>To the right Worſhipfull, and his very good friends, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Stephens,</hi> and to his good and vertuous Wife, M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
                     <hi>Elizabeth Stephens, R. W.</hi> wiſheth all happineſſe both in this world, and in the world <hi>to come.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Sermon following, there are lapped vp (right Worſhipfull) ſome twelue points of diuine inspiration, which are moſt needfull in this corrupt age wherein we liue, of all mens due and deepe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The firſt is, that Christ and his Church are contracted together in a thriſe bleſſed marriage, The ſecond is, that the Church doth beare a tender &amp; hearty loue towards Chriſt her bridegrome. The third is, that the eſtate or condition of Gods childe is the beſt eſtate or condition in all the world. The fourth is, that Chirſt himſelfe is there teaching of men, where his word is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught &amp; deliuered vnto men. The fift is, that the fruit &amp; benefit of Gods word is imparted onely vnto the Saints. The ſixt is, that the beſt that are, are to be taught and ſchooled in the wayes of God. The ſeauenth is, that Chriſt doth loue his Church and people well. The eight is, that the Church of God is faire and beautifull in the eyes of Chriſt. The ninth is, that holy Chriſtians need not the mediation of Angels or Saints departed this life, for the oblation of their prayers vnto the Almighty. The tenth is, that the ſpouſe of Chriſt is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too careleſſe of Chriſt, and falls a ſleepe in the bed of carnall delights. The eleuenth is, that Chriſtians muſt not continue in their ſins, but ariſe from the ſame &amp; leaue them. The twelft and last is, that all that doe belong to Chriſt, muſt leaue this world &amp; goe after Chriſt. Theſe points are handled, ſeauen of them more at large, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>profeſſo,</hi> by way of doctrines, but the other fiue more ſuccinctly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on certaine accidentall occaſions. At your leaſure (I pray you) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them, I doubt not, but that you haue your portions in them. The text from whence they are drawne may well be applied vnto you, for euery word therein doth fit you well. One part of it you may
<pb facs="tcp:8504:24"/>ſpeake (with the Church) of Chriſt: and the other part of it you may heare (with the Church) from Christ. And as ſome things in it may comfort you, ſo other things alſo in it may excite you. The Appellations may be your conſolations, and the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations may be your excitations.</p>
                  <p>In the world there are many euils, yea in the congregation of the righteous there are too many infirmities. Our loue to Chriſt is too cold, it muſt be kindled. Our attendance at the gates of wiſed me is too ſeldome, it muſt be doubled. Ourfailing in our duties is too great, it muſt be leſſened. Our ſight in ſeeing the loue of Chriſt towards vs is too Diuine, it must be cleered. Our beauty in the inner man is too ſmall, it muſt be increaſed. Our drowſines in good things is too heauy, it muſt be lightned. Our continuance in ſinne is too long, it must be ſhortned. Our cleauing to this world is too ſtrong, it muſt be weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Finally our following afte Chriſt is too ſlow, it muſt be haſtned. To further this heauenly work this little booke may help vs, for moſt of the things therein are touched, and vrged vpon vs with forcible reaſons of perſwaſion: In token of my good will, and the vnfained loue which I beare vnto you both, I here preſent it vnto you both, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate it to your Worſhips. The God almighty giue it a bleſſing, &amp; and make it effectuall vnto the ſoules of men. I will not trouble you with many words, but draw to an end. As you haue begun well, ſo proccede, &amp; let your good works be more at the laſt, then at the firſt. Be ſtill for God in all his wayes, and God will ſtill be for you in all your wayes. Aduance him and hee will aduance you, protect his Saints, and ſhelter them: refreſh the deare members of Chriſt and nouriſh them; ſo ſhall you heare this ſweet ſentence pronounced vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yount the laſt: <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit ye the kingdome prepared for you from the foundations of the world.</hi> And ſo I end and commit you and all yours to the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous protection of that good God, that doth watch ouer you; beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo to multiply his graces vpon you, that you may ſee many good and happy dayes in this wretched world, and enioy euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe in the bleſſed world to come.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Worſhips in all holy duties to be commanded.</hi> Richard Webb.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8504:24"/>
                  <head>THE FIRST SERMON, OF CHRISTIAN LOVE.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Canticles 2. verſe 10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>My welbeloued ſpake, and ſaid vnto me, Ariſe, my loue, my faire one, and come thy way.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I was pondering with my ſelfe, what text I might beſt take for this time and for this place: it pleaſed the good and gracious hand of our God, to direct me to this portion of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writ, as containing in it matters moſt correſpondent to the day now celebrated, &amp; to this worthy aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly now congregated. For as the day is now kept for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Chriſt, in memoriall of his Aſcention from the earth to the heauens; and as this aſſembly is an aſſembly of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who muſt ariſe after Chriſt: ſo this text in hand is a text of Chriſt and of his Church. Of Chriſt, as it were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die aſcended; yet in mercie ſpeaking to his Church: of the Church yet below, yet in dutie to aſcend after Chriſt. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof I doubt not, but that thoſe things, which ſhall be now ſpoken, will be vnto you moſt ſweet and profitable, like apples of gold with pictures of ſiluer, according to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> Aphoriſme, in <hi>Prou.</hi> 25.11 where he ſaith, <hi>A word
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8504:25"/>ſpoken in his place is like apples of gold, with pictures of ſiluer.</hi> But not to inſiſt any further vpon other matters by way of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, I will deſcend vnto my Text.</p>
                  <p>In the verſes next going before, it is declared, what mercie the Lord Ieſus Chriſt did ſhew vnto his Church, in comming vnto her notwithſtanding all her ſins. Though her iniquities were like to hils &amp; mountains, which might iuſtly haue ſtaied him from comming vnto her; yet he in the multitudes of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſions towards her, was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, like a Roe, or yong Hart, to leape or skip ouer them all, and in kindneſſe to draw neere vnto her, notwithſtanding the ſame. And howſoeuer he did not, as it were, come openly into her houſe, diſcloſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto her plainely and fully, as it were face to face: yet he did ſtand behinde her wall, and there looked in vpon her through the grates and windowes of his Goſpell, reueiling himſelfe ſo far vnto her, as was needfull and conuenient both for her preſent conſolation, and alſo for her future ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>The which that wee might the better conceiue, ſhee her ſelfe giues teſtimonie of him, and ſhewes what words he did vſe vnto her: and this ſhee doth in this preſent verſe, which now we haue in hand. In which, if we conſider of all matters, well, we ſhall finde two principall points concerning that Goſpell ſpoken off before, by which our Sauiour did diſcouer himſelfe vnto his Spouſe. The firſt is concerning the perſons, whom it doth reſpect. The ſecond is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the matter whereof it doth conſiſt. The perſons, whom it doth reſpect, are of two ſorts, namely, the perſon that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the perſon that is taught. The perſon that teacheth, is Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, her beſt beloued. Howſoeuer he doth vſe man, as an inſtrument in this worke, yet hee himſelfe is the principall agent therein. It is he chiefely that doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and teach his people. The perſon that is taught, is the Church her ſelfe. Her welbeloued ſpake and directed his words vnto her, and not to others. Others indeed may haue the crummes and bones that fall from his table, like dogges, but the bread and good fleſh, that is vpon the table it ſelfe, is prouided only for her, and her children.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8504:25"/>
                  <p>The matter whereof the Goſpell doth conſiſt, brancheth it ſelfe into two parts. The firſt noteth out, how well Chriſt is affected towards his Church, in that he calls her his loue, and his faire one. The ſecond ſetteth down what dutie the Church doth owe to Chriſt, in that he wills her to Ariſe, and come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; both are brought in by the figure <hi>Proſopopeia.</hi> For the Church doth bring in Chriſt himſelfe ſpeaking, &amp; vttering al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in effect, as it were theſe words vnto her. O deare &amp; welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Virgin, whom I haue choſen among al the daughters of men to be my Spouſe, and whom I haue made faire and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, euen white and ruddie, with the water and bloud which I ſhed for thy ſake, and with my Spirit, whom I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon thee for thy good: doe not now lie weltring in thy ſinnes, nor continue any longer in the bed of thy carnall delights, but ariſe and leaue the ſame: and conſider, that I haue done ſo much for thee, and doe make ſuch an account of thee; delay not the time, but make haſt and come away: forſake all the baſe affaires of this life, and the ſweet delights of the fleſh, and addreſſe thy ſelfe vnto the conſummation of our moſt ioyfull mariage, thou being euer there, where I am, and alwayes endeuouring to doe, as I doe.</p>
                  <p>This Verſe then in ſumme,
<note place="margin">Summe.</note> comprehendeth in it nothing elſe, but the Churches report, of that which Chriſt ſpake to her, when he beheld her by his Goſpell, through the cage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherein I pray remember with me theſe two points:
<note place="margin">Part.</note> firſt, her words to him; then ſecondly, his words to her. Her words of him ſpend themſelues in two things: the firſt is an Appellation, the ſecond is a Declaration. The Appellation in the firſt word, <hi>My beloued:</hi> The Declaration in the next words, <hi>ſpake and ſaid to me:</hi> containing in it, firſt, his teaching, vnder theſe words, <hi>ſpake and ſaid,</hi> then ſecondly, the perſon whom he taught, in this word, <hi>to me.</hi> Now of theſe, by Gods grace in order.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My welbeloued.]</hi> This Appellation, or title, the Church might well giue vnto Chriſt, in a twofold reſpect. Firſt, actiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe ſhe did loue him well, then paſſiuely, becauſe ſhee was beloued of him well. For there was a ſingular loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8504:26"/>them, the one towards the other. But yet this doth not note out the full or whole reaſon of this Appellation, or title, which is often vſed in this booke, ſometimes by the Church to Chriſt, and ſometimes againe by Chriſt to the Church. Doubtleſſe, the reaſon of it is twofold. The one is in regard of their mutuall loue; the other of their intended marriage. For Chriſt and his Church are brought in, in this Canticle, as two Paramours, who are in loue one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and who in time conuenient doe purpoſe to marry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Of their loues afterwards; a word or two of their marriage by the way. As the ſame is oftentimes ſpoken of in the Word, and moſt liuely ſhadowed out vnto vs, in the 45. Pſalme, vnder the type and figure of <hi>Salomons</hi> marriage with King <hi>Phara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hs</hi> daughter of Egypt: ſo you muſt know, it is not yet finiſhed, but deferred till the day of Iudgement; as may well bee collected out of <hi>Reuelat.</hi> 19.7. where theſe words are ſet downe to bee ſpoken in the end of the world: <hi>Let vs be glad and resoyce, and giue glorie to him, for the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Lambe is come, and his wife hath made her ſelfe ready.</hi> Here in this world is the Contract alone; the marriage is kept for the world to come. As heere men and women firſt haue their contracts, or eſpouſals, then afterwards their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and reall marriages, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> were firſt eſpouſed before they came together, <hi>Muth.</hi> 1.11. So would the Lord obſerue the ſame order of proceeding in the vnion of theſe two great and Princely States; of his Sonne on the one ſide, being the glory and ornament of heauen; and of the Church on the otherſide, being the praiſe and beautie of the earth. They muſt firſt be contracted, then after they muſt be married. This Contract of theirs muſt be conſidered two wayes. One way, as it is made with the whole Church in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; another way, as it is made with the particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof. As it is made with the whole Church in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, it was from the beginning of the world, euen immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately vpon <hi>Adams</hi> fall, when God did promiſe him that the ſeed of the woman ſhould breake the Serpents head, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. For then was this marriage in queſtion, and it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8504:26"/>vpon betweene God and <hi>Adam,</hi> for the holy poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to come. But now as it is made with the particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, it is at all times; for there are ſome daily vnited vnto Chriſt. And this their Contract is made two manner of wayes. The one is ſacramentally, and that is, when they are baptiſed into the name of Chriſt. The other is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and that is, when they are regenerated, and doe beginne to beleeue in Chriſt, and depend vpon him ſolely and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their ſaluation. Now Chriſt and the faithfull being thus contracted together, do loue each other moſt entirely (as contracted perſons ought to doe) and long ſtill for the day of their marriage, that ſo they may enioy one the other in full perfection. In regard whereof, I ſay, they giue this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or appellation of <hi>Welbeloued</hi> one vnto the other, often in this booke, which is wholely ſpent in a manner in deſcribing out ſuch loue tokens as paſſe betwixt them, to wit, from the day of their eſpouſals, vnto the day of their marriage.</p>
                  <p>But paſſing thus their marriage, let vs come vnto their loues: the firſt is of the Church towards Chriſt, in this word, <hi>My welbeloued:</hi> the next is of Chriſt towards his Church, in the other word, <hi>my loue,</hi> the which I will referre to his due place, and handle it then when I come vnto it.</p>
                  <p>For the former of theſe,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> in that the Church doth call Chriſt her welbeloued; as for other cauſes, ſo for this, becauſe ſhe did loue him well: we are taught this Doctrine, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member of the Church muſt truely, and vnfainedly loue the Lord Ieſus. So did <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, his loue was ſo great to Chriſt, that in the end he died for Chriſt; ſo that he might well ſay to Chriſt, when he did aske of him this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Whether he did loue him or no? <hi>Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Lord, thou knoweſt that I loue thee, Ioh.</hi> 21.15. So did <hi>Mary</hi> the great ſinner; her loue was ſo large to Chriſt, that ſhe did many things, which did iuſtly honor Chriſt: ſhe came to the place where be was, and brought a boxe of oyntment; ſhe ſtood at his ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him weeping; ſhe waſhed his ſect with teares, ſhee did wipe them with the haires of her head; ſhee did kiſſe them with her mouth, and annoint them with the ointment: ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8504:27"/>that Chriſt might well ſay of her, and to her praiſe, that ſhee loued him much, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.47. So did the ſcattered Iewes, that were Saints; their loue was ſo vpright towards Chriſt, that though they did neuer ſee Chriſt with the mortall eves of their bodies, yet they did loue Chriſt, and ſo ſet their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vpon him, that they did reioyce in him with ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and glorious: ſo that <hi>Peter</hi> might well commend them in this reſpect, for their loue to Chriſt, as indeed hee doth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. So in a word, did the Church, and ſtill doth: her loue is ſo hot, and ſtrong to Chriſt, that nothing ſhall part her from Chriſt; neither perſecutions on the one ſide, nor promotions on the other, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6 7. So that ſhe might truely ſay theſe words of her ſelfe; <hi>Stay me with flagons, and comfort me with apples, for I am ſicke of loue, Cant.</hi> 2.5. Thus then ſhould all the righteous loue Chriſt, as indeed they do, witneſſe the Spouſe her ſelfe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3.</p>
                  <p>The reaſons to draw vs on to this loue are foure.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                     </label> The firſt is, becauſe he hath loued vs; according to that of <hi>Iohn,</hi> in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19. <hi>We loue him, becauſe hath loued vs first: Inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus eum, non praeuenimus,</hi> We found him, not preuented him. <hi>Dilexit enim non existentes imo reſistentes,</hi> For he loued vs when we were not; yea, when we were his enemies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.10. The Church doth declare in <hi>Cantic.</hi> 2.4. that this is a ſpeciall meanes to draw the affections of men after Chriſt; for there his loue is compared to a banner: for as by the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or enſigne, the ſouldiers are drawne to their owne Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and colours; ſo by the loue of Ieſus Chriſt, as by a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or enſigne, are all the choſen ones drawne to Chriſt: in which reſpect the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſhew, that the loue of Chriſt hath a certaine power or force to conſtraine, or to compell men, when he ſaith, for the <hi>loue of Christ constras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, becauſe he is very kinde and bountifull to ſuch as do loue him, according to that which is in the Pſalme, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.25. where all the Saints of God, are willed to loue the Lord vpon this ground, becauſe he doth preſerue them that doe it, as well as deſtroy the wicked that are their enemies.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8504:27"/>Chriſt is not a wilderneſſe, nor a land of darkeneſſe to ſuch as loue him, but a fountaine of all happineſſe. He is content to come home, as it were, to them, and to dwell with them in their ſoules, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.23. Yea, hee doth prouide ſuch large things, and excellent matters for them, as are altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, and paſt our vnderſtanding, as witneſſeth the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. in theſe words, <hi>The things which the eye hath not ſeene, neither the eare hath heard, neither came into mans heart;</hi> are, which God hath prepared for them that loue him. Surely vpon this conſideration, <hi>Mary,</hi> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of before, was much affected to Chriſt: becauſe ſhe ſaw that Chriſt was kinde to her, and very liberall, in pardoning all her ſinnes, which were many; ſhe could not but loue him much for that cauſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.47. So the Virgins fell in loue with Chriſt, vpon the view and remembrance of ſuch bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits as do come to men by Chriſt, as we are taught in <hi>Cantic.</hi> 1.2. in theſe words, <hi>Becauſe of the ſauonr of thy good ointments, thy name is as an ointment powred out, therefore the Virgins loue thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third is, becauſe he is moſt excellent in himſelfe, and moſt worthy of all our loues, as being the chiefeſt of ten thouſands, <hi>Cantic.</hi> 5.10. And this is true in many reſpects: Firſt, for his beauties ſake: Secondly, for his riches ſake: Thirdly, for his parentage ſake: Fourthly, for his wiſdomes ſake: Laſtly, for his loues ſake. In this world we loue ſome, and marry with them, onely becauſe they are faire and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull: ſome, onely becauſe they are rich and wealthie: ſome, onely becauſe they are of a Noble and Honourable houſe: ſome, onely becauſe they are wiſe and prudent: ſome, laſtly, becauſe they are louing and kinde. Now how Chriſt is faire and beautifull, you may ſee by this, becauſe he is the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the glorie of his Father, and the ingrauen forme of his Perſon, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>brewes</hi> 1.3. How he is rich and wealthie, you may ſee by this, becauſe he is the heire of all the world. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. How he is noble and honorable, you may ſee by this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is the King of Kings. and Lord of Lords, <hi>Reuelat.</hi> 19.16. How he is wiſe and prudent, you may ſee by this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8504:28"/>in him are hid all the treaſures of knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, <hi>Coleſſ.</hi> 2.3. And laſtly, how hee is louing and kinde, you may ſee by this, becauſe he died for vs to redeeme vs, and doth ſtill cheriſh and nouriſh vs, as his owne bodie, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.2.29. When the Church had commended her wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued, and had ſet him out in his orient colours before the eyes of men, thoſe that did before deſpiſe him, fell in ſome loue with him, and offered their ſeruice to the Church to ioyne with her to ſeeke him out, <hi>Cantic.</hi> 5. and laſt verſe. Thus his excellencie is as an Adamant to draw vs, that are irons, vnto him.</p>
                  <p>The fourth and laſt is, becauſe thoſe that will not loue him, ſhall periſh and be damned: if any man loue not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16, 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, let him bee hanged vp on high, the Lord doth come; or as it is tranſlated in our Engliſh Bible, <hi>Let him be had in exceration,</hi> yea excommunicate to death. Hereof is that ſaying in <hi>Luke,</hi> Chapter 19.27. vttered by our Sauiour himſelſe, <hi>Theſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould raigne ouer them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me.</hi> When <hi>Niniuch</hi> heard, that ſhee muſt bee deſtroyed within fortie dayes, ſhe repented immediately vpon it in ſack-cloth and aſhes, and did forſake her euill wayes, and turned from the wickedneſſe that was in her hands, <hi>Ionah</hi> 3.8 So wee hearing that we ſhall be deſtroyed, vnleſſe we loue the Lord Ieſus; it muſt awaken vs, like a mightie thunder-clap from heauen, and cauſe vs out of hand to affect him.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee the reaſons,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> now let vs come to the vſes; they are in number three. The firſt is for reprehenſion, the ſecond for conſolation, and the third for admonition. In the firſt place they are heere reprehended, who care little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all for the Lord Ieſus. Certainly, whether they be Iewes or Gentiles, bond or free, male or female, their eſtate is moſt lamentable, we may quake euen to thinke of it: for no leſſe then dampation it ſelfe (as was intimated before) is their portion and inheritance for euermore. They will perhaps conſeſſe, that Murther, Adultery, Idolatry, Witchcraft, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8504:28"/>ſuch notorious crimes are ſinnes indeede, and that they doe deſerue euerlaſting puniſhments: but let them now at the laſt both ſee and confeſſe, that this is indeede a great ſinne, not to loue the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and ſuch an one, as will damne them for euer, vnleſſe they doe repent for it in time: and therefore let them leaue it, and amend it, mourning and lamenting as bitterly for this fault, as for any other ſinne whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond place, they are here comforted, who haue made choiſe of Ieſus Chriſt to be their husband, and haue ſet their whole heart &amp; ſoule vpon him. In this they haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a worthie duty, and ſuch as may bring vnto them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation at all times. For now will Chriſt reſpect them moſt gratiouſly for euermore, and alwayes doe them good, as who is much delighted in their loue, according to his owne words vnto the Church in <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.10. When heſaith: <hi>My ſiſter, my Spouſe, how faire is thy loue? How much better is thy loue, then wine? And the ſauour of thine ointments then all ſpices?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the third and laſt place, all of vs are here admoniſhed to doe that which the ſpouſe did, namely to loue Chriſt well, wee muſt take him for our onely bridegrome, and accept of none but him. I doubt not, but that you ſhall haue many ſuitors to the contrary. For the world, and the fleſh, and the deuill will be labouring ſtill to draw you vnto them, and ſend vnto you, as it were, many ſolicitors for that end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, time after time: but beware, I pray, giue not your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents vnto them, neither harken vnto their voyces, though they ſing as ſweetly as the Sirens or Mermaides are repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to doe. O ſtop your eares againſt them, as <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes,</hi> is feigned by ſome to doe: in this point be like to the deafe adder, who will not heare the charmer, though hee charme neuer ſoſweetly. Giue entertainement, I beſeech you, to the Lord of glory, and let him be your welbeloued. For this end and purpoſe remember the reaſons before going. What? Shall hee beginne to loue vs, and ſhall not wee loue him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? What? Is hee rich and bountifull to all ſuch as doe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8504:29"/>loue him, beſtowing large benefits dayly vpon them? And ſhall not wee our ſelues loue him? What? is he moſt worthy of the loue of all perſons, as being moſt faire and beautifull, as being moſt rich and wealthy, as being moſt noble, and honourable, as being moſt wiſe and prudent, as being laſtly moſt louing and kinde? and yet ſhall not vvee loue him? What? in the laſt place? Will he deſtroy all thoſe that ſhall not loue him, and bring them to a perpetuali deſolation? and yet for all that, ſhall not we loue him? Oh my brethren, let vs remember our ſelues, and be vviſe at the laſt for our owne good: let vs not wilfully caſt away our ſelues, but ſaue our ſoules from the euils to come. My ſuite vnto you at this time, is for your loues for Chriſt my Maiſter.</p>
                  <p>If he were (that I may ſo ſpeake without offence to any) a deformed perſon, like to <hi>Therſites.</hi> I would not wiſh you to loue him: if hee vvere a poore man, like to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> I would not wiſh you to affect him: if he were a baſe brat, like to <hi>Abimilick,</hi> I would not wiſh you to follow him: if hee vvere a fooliſh fellow, like to <hi>Nabal,</hi> I would not wiſh you to reſpect him: finally, if hee were a cruell beaſt, like to <hi>Nero,</hi> I would not wiſh you to embrace him. But now ſeeing hee is beautifull, rich, honourable, wiſe, and louely, aboue all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with mortall men; I would wiſh you, yea moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intreat you, that you vvould loue him, affect him, follow him, reſpect him, and embrace him, and that for euer and euer. Euery wiſe man in chooſing a Maiſter to himſelfe doth refuſe three ſorts of perſons, namely: his enemy, his fellow, and his ſeruant. Hee that ſerueth the deuill, ſerueth his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; he that ſerueth his fleſh, ſerueth his fellow, and he that ſerueth the vvorld, ſerueth his ſeruant. Becauſe the former of theſe doe argue fooliſhneſſe and want of wits, and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two baſeneſſe and want of courage, I hope, that none of you, who are wiſe and couragious, vvill now ſerue any of them, but that from henceforth Ieſus Chriſt ſhall be your Lord and Maiſter alone.</p>
                  <p>But here that I may not looſe my labour, and ſo fiſh in vaine, but bring you all rather vvithin the compaſſe of my
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8504:29"/>ner, and ſo take many fiſhes; giue me leaue to giue an anſwere to three ſorts of perſons. The firſt is of thoſe that make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt the ſtate of ſuch as loue Chriſt. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is of thoſe that boaſt of their loue towards Chriſt, and yet doe want it. The third is of thoſe that would be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, what manner of loue it is, that is pleaſing to CHRIST. For the firſt of theſe, many are vnwilling (as dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth teach vs) to ioyne themſelues in a true knot of marriage loue, becauſe they thinke, that their eſtate is moſt miſerable, vvho are ſo ioyned to him in loue: and that firſt, becauſe the deuill doth perſue them, <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.13. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe the world doth hate them, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.19. Thirdly, becauſe Chriſt himſelfe doth correct them, <hi>Reu.</hi> 3.19.</p>
                  <p>But let none of vs be deceiued.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> The condition of the CHVRCH is farre better, then the world doth take it to be. Hearken vvhat <hi>Dauid</hi> doth ſay of it. <hi>Bleſſed is that nation, whoſe God is the Lord, euen the people, ſaith hee, that hee hath choſen for his inheritance. Pſal.</hi> 33.12. For this cauſe did he make this requeſt vnto the Almighty, ſaying, <hi>Remember me, O Lord, with the fauour of thy people, viſit mee with thy ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that I may ſee the filicitie of thy choſen, and reioyce in the ioy of thy people, and glory with thine inheritance. Pſal.</hi> 106. 4 5. Surely I dare here pawne my ſoule and life, that there is no eſtate in the vvhole vvorld ſo good as the eſtate of Gods people, and of ſuch, as doe loue Chriſt: the vvhich I will make euident vnto you, by Gods good grace, in a few words.</p>
                  <p>We account, as you know, thoſe to be maruellous happy perſons, and their eſtates to he the beſt of all. Firſt, who are out of debt. Secondly, who fare vvell. Thirdly, who goe fine. Fourthly, who are attended vpon by many ſeruants. Fiftly, who are able to giue to others. Sixtly, who are out of law and trouble hauing peace within and without. Seuenth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who inioy their health. Eightly, who are in authority of high place to command or rule. Finally, who haue great lands and poſſeſſions. Hee that hath all theſe is a complet bleſſed man vvith vs. For hee wanteth nothing, that may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8504:30"/>tend to the perfection of his happy eſtate in the iudgement of fleſh and blood. Now thoſe that are the Lords people, and doe loue Chriſt well, as they ſhould doe, haue all theſe. Firſt, they are out of debt, for Chriſt hath diſcharged them from all their ſinnes, which are their debts, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. Secondly, they fare well: they haue a rich table: for the Lord of hoſts doth make for all his people a feaſt of fat things, euen a feaſt of fined wines, and of fat things, full of marrow, of wines fined and purified. He alſo doth ſatisfie them with the fatneſſe of his houſe, and giue them drinke out of the riuers of his pleaſures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.2. <hi>Eſay</hi> 25.6. Thirdly, they goe fine: for they are clothed with the golden and ſilken robes of Ieſus Chriſt and of his Spirit. The woman, whereunto the Church is compared, is clothed with the Sunne, hauing the Moone vnder her feete, and a crowne of twelue Starres vpon her head, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12.1. So the Spouſe or Wife of Chriſt, is ſaid to be arrayed with pure fine linnen, and ſhining, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.8. Fourthly, they are attended vpon by many ſeruants: for the gloricus Angels that are aboue, do euermore waite vpon them, as nurſes doe vpon children, to keepe them ſtill in ſafetie and in peace, and to doe ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices vnto them, as are needfull for them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.11.12. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.14. So that there is no Noble man in the Land, that hath a goodlier traine to attend vpon him, then Gods childe hath. Fiftly, they are able to giue to others: for God hath beſtowed vpon them ſuch a treaſure of grace, that they are able, not onely to edifie themſelues, but others alſo in the wayes of their ſaluation, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.7.16.</p>
                  <p>This is worthily ſeene, as in other ſtories, ſo in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> who brought great light and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding vnto <hi>Apollos</hi> himſelfe, who was an eloquent man, and mightie in the Scriptures, when they tooke him vnto them, and expounded vnto him the way of God more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.26. Sixtly, they are out of Law and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and haue peace both within and without: for God is now reconciled to them, and ſo they haue a peace, not onely with God himſelfe, and his creatures, but alſo with themſelues
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8504:30"/>and in their owne ſoules and conſciences, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14.16. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. Seauenthly, they enioy their health: for their ſoules within are ſound and well, as who doe not ſo much liue in themſelues, as in Chriſt. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. nor yet ſhrinke away from the Commandements of their God, but carefully ſtill obſerue the ſame, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 44.17.18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.39. They goe as it were, from ſtrength to ſtrength, till they appeare perfect in Sion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7. And their good workes are more at the laſt, then at the firſt, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelat.</hi> 2.19. Eightly, they are in authoritie of high place, to command or rule: for Chriſt hath made them Kings and Prieſts vnto God, euen his Father, <hi>Reuelat.</hi> 1.6. So that they are great Officers and Commanders in the world, like Prieſts and Kings, which haue the Chiefeſt roomes of all. Laſtly, they haue great lands and poſſeſſions: for all the world is theirs: whether it be <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> or the world, or life, or death, whether they be things preſent, or things to come, euen all are yours, ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to the godly <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Peter</hi> tels vs, that there is an inheritance immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, which is vndefiled, and fadeth not away, reſerued in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for vs, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.4. And our Sauiour ſheweth, that God his Father hath prepared for vs a Kingdome from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34. Wherefore by this wee may ſee, vnleſſe we will wilfully be blinde, and meaſure euery thing by the narrow ſpan of our owne naturall reaſon, that the condition of Gods childe is the beſt condition in the world, and that they are moſt happie perſons, who are vnited vnto Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But what then ſhall we ſay vnto their afflictions, which are many in this world? haue not wee iuſt cauſe to reiect Ieſus Chriſt for them, and to accept of ſome other before him? No, in no caſe: Firſt, becauſe they doe not impaire our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie eſtate, but rather better the ſame; and that in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: Firſt, becauſe they doe not take away the fruit and benefit of thoſe outward goods, which are taken away from vs, but rather encreaſe them: for they make vs to enioy them an hundred fold more, as it is in <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.30. So that in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8504:31"/>middeſt of them all, we haue great ioy and comfort, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.41. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.34. Secondly, becauſe they ſerue to purge vs from our droſſe and corruption, that we might be made partakers of Gods holineſſe, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.10. and not be damned with the world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. Thirdly and laſtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are meanes to augment our happines in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens aboue, and to worke out for vs a farre more excellent and eternall weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this time, wherein we now liue in this world, is not the time of our marriage, but the time onely of our eſpouſalls. As yet we are not with Chriſt, but we liue, as it were, with our friends, among whom wee may be euilly intreated, and be hardly dealt withall, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was among his owne brethren. A poore Virgin (you know) that is but onely betrothed to a noble perſon, of great ſtate and wealth, and not yet married vnto him, may liue but a ſimple and miſerable kinde of life, vntill the day of their marriage doth come. For as ſhee may fare and lie hard, and be but meantly attired in her fathers houſe, who is but a poore man, and vnable to maintaine her better; ſo ſhee may fall ſicke of loue, and withall enter into many doubtfull thoughts, and feares, leſt her beloued ſhould caſt her off, and preferre ſome other noble perſon before her: whereby it comes to paſſe, that her heart is much woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and her ſpirit euen vexed to the death it ſelfe. Yet for all this, ſhee had no iuſt cauſe to haue refuſed him at the firſt, neither yet hath any to reiect him now at the laſt; conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eſpecially, that this her trouble will ſhortly end, and much continuall ioy come in the place thereof.</p>
                  <p>So after the ſame manner, though heere in this world wee haue ſome afflictions, yet we are not for that cauſe to alienate our ſelues from the Sauiour of the world; eſpecially conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that he will end them quickely, and come and marrie with vs, at what time we ſhall haue ioy and happineſſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto of thoſe that make exceptions againſt the ſtate of ſuch as loue Chriſt. Now let vs come to thoſe that boaſt of their loue towards Chriſt, and yet doe want it.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8504:31"/>
                  <p>We finde by experience, that there are too many ſuch, in all places, whereſoeuer we come. Though they hate him in their ſoules, yet they will loue him in their words. They can crie out and ſay, <hi>We loue the Lord Ieſus Christ, as well as the best of you all: he is not worthy to liue that doth not loue him; it were well that the ground would open to ſincke him in,</hi> &amp;c. Thus can wicked men giue good words, but where are their workes. Surely in this corrupt age of ours wee can talke much, but walke but a little; word it much, but worke it but a little: our mouthes are bigger then our hands, which is a thing mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous in nature: as well ſaid Saint <hi>Bernard, Monſtroſa res eſt, ſedes prima, vita ima, lingua magniloqua &amp; manus otiſſa, ſermo multus, fructus nullus:</hi> It is a monſtrous thing to haue the chiefeſt roome, and to liue the baſeſt life; to ſpeake much with the tongue, and to doe nothing with the hand; to vſe many words, and to bring forth no fruit. But as <hi>Iames</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaid, <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy workes, Iam.</hi> 2.18. So may I ſay, Shew me thy Ioue by thy workes. There are foure things in all heartie and ſound louers, which muſt needs be in thee, if thou doeſt loue Chriſt aright. The firſt is, that they long ſtill to be ioyned together, and to enioy one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The nature of loue is ſuch, that wee deſire ſtill the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of that which is loued. <hi>Ammon</hi> was very ſick through loue, and his fleſh did pine away, becauſe hee could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy his ſiſter <hi>Thamar,</hi> whom he loued, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.2. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, that they are bountifull and liberall one vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Loue, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. is bountifull. So was <hi>Booz</hi> to <hi>Ruth,</hi> whom hee loued. <hi>Ruth</hi> 3.15. and ſo was the Centurion to the Iewes, whom hee made much of, for hee built them a Synagogue, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.5. The third is, that they are obſequious and obedient one vnto the other. Loue can hardly deny any worke, which the partie beloued doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Hereof was it, that <hi>Delilah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Sampſon,</hi> in <hi>Iudges</hi> 16.15. <hi>How canst thou ſay, I loue thee, when thine heart is not with me? thou haſt mocked me theſe three times, and haſt not told me wherein thy great ſtrength lieth.</hi> The fourth and laſt is tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerance, or enduring of troubles one for the other: for the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8504:32"/>loue, that <hi>Iacob</hi> did beare to <hi>Rahel,</hi> ſeauen yeares of hard ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude ſeemed but a ſhort time, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.20. And for the loue that <hi>Sechem</hi> did beare to <hi>Dinah,</hi> he was content to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and to ſuffer the cutting of his fleſh, though it were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry painfull vnto him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.19.</p>
                  <p>Now in all theſe things, examine thy loue towards Chriſt. In the firſt place, tell me, doeſt thou long to be with Chriſt? Art thou willing to die, and to leaue this world, to goe vnto him? Doeſt thou wiſh with the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, to be with him? <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.25. Art thou deſirous to haue him come to Iudgement Doeſt thou cry out with the Spouſe, <hi>Come Lord Ieſus, come quickly? Ren.</hi> 22.17.20 In the ſecond place, tel me, Doſt thou beſtow any thing vpon Chriſt? Art thou willing to let go thy goods and riches for the honor of Chriſt? Art thou readie to relieue his Saints, according to their need, and thy abilitie? Doeſt thou ioyne with others in building vp his Church, and in beſtowing ſome maintenance vpon his worſhip? In the third place, tell me, Doeſt thou obey him, and doe according to his Commandements? Art thou readie with <hi>Abraham,</hi> to leaue thine ovvne countrey, and to goe vvhither he ſhall ſend thee? Wilt thou forſake that vvhich hee doth forbid, and follovv that vvhich hee doth command? <hi>If yee loue me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>beepe my Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, Ioh.</hi> 14.15. And a little after he ſaith againe, <hi>If any man loue me, he will keepe my Word, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 23. So that thoſe loue not Chriſt, vvho doe not keepe his Commandements. In the fourth and laſt place, tell mee, Doeſt thou ſuffer any trouble or miſerie for Chriſts ſake? Art thou vvell pleaſed to take vp thy croſſe to goe after him? Canſt thou be content to die for his ſake, as the Prophets and Apoſtles haue done? By theſe markes or tokens wee may know whether wee loue Chriſt or no: if we haue them, we loue him; but if we haue them not, wee loue him not, howſoeuer wee perſwade our ſolues, or boaſt before others to the contrarie.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much of the ſecond ſort, namely of thoſe that vaunt of their loue towards Chriſt, and yet doe want it. Now let vs come to the third and laſt ſort, which is of thoſe that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8504:32"/>would be informed what manner of loue it is that is pleaſing to Chriſt. In it you muſt obſerue foure remarkable qualities. The firſt is, that it muſt be great and not ſmall: we muſt loue him more then our fathers, or mothers, or brothren, or ſiſters, or husbands, or wiues, or lands, or goods, or life it ſelfe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Lzk.</hi> 14.26. The ſecond is, that it muſt be ſingular and not common: we muſt loue onely Chriſt, and none elſe, we muſt not ioyne others with him: <hi>Whom haue I in heauen</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 73.25.) <hi>but thee? and I haue deſired none in the earth with thee.</hi> Well therefore ſaid the Church, in <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Shew me, O thou, whom my ſoule loueth, where thou feedest, where thou lieſt at noone; for why ſhould I be as ſhe that turneth aſide to the flockes of thy companions?</hi> Her care was onely to goe after Chriſt. We cannot ſerue God and <hi>Mimmon</hi> together, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.24. We muſt not part our loue, Chriſt muſt haue all: as the woman by Gods law muſt haue but one husband; ſo the Church muſt haue but one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. Doubtleſſe, as an honeſt man cannot endure that another man ſhould haue a portion in his wife: ſo will not Chriſt endure, that any other ſhould haue with him a portion in his Church, for he is a iealous God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. The third is, that it muſt be totall, and not partiall: we muſt loue him, not with the loue of the ſoule alone, or with the loue of the body alone, but with the loue both of body and ſoule toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Ye are bought with a price</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20) <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore glorifie God in your bodie, and in your ſpirit, for they are Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whereas the ſoule and body doe conſiſt of many parts, our Sauiour muſt haue the loue of all thoſe parts. <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with thy ſtrength,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5. So that Chriſt muſt not haue onely the loue of the eye, to behold his workes; the loue of the eare, to liſten to his words; the loue of the tongue, to talke of his wonders; the loue of the feet, to goe to his Temple; the loue of the hands, to doe his buſineſſe; the loue of the memorie, to remember him; the loue of the minde, to plod vpon him; and the loue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8504:33"/>of the heart to long after him; but hee muſt haue all theſe loues together. The fourth and laſt is, that it muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, and not temporall. We muſt not loue him for a time alone, as for certaine dayes, weekes, monthes, or yeares but we muſt loue him beyond all time, euen for euer and euer. <hi>Be thou faithfull vnto the death,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt to the Church of the <hi>Smirnsans, Reu.</hi> 2.10.) <hi>and I will giue thee the crowne of life.</hi> The Spouſe doth tell vs in <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6.7. Firſt that her loue is ſo well grounded towards Chriſt, that nothing can ouer come it, or take it away from her; neither perſecutions on the one ſide, nor worldly promotions on the other. Surely, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can turne God from louing them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.39. ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can turne them from louing God, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Act.</hi> 21.13. In this reſpect they are like the Vine, Oliue, and Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, that would not leaue their goodneſſe, to go to be aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced aboue the other trees, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9.9. &amp;c. So that in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, we muſt follow Chriſts Commandement, when he ſaid vnto his Diſciples, <hi>Abide in my loue, Ioh.</hi> 15 9.</p>
                  <p>Thus you haue heard in a few words, what manner of loue it is that we muſt beare towards Chriſt, when we doe accept of him for our Husband. Examine now in your owne ſoules, whether you haue this loue or no: if you haue it, bleſſe God for it; but if you haue it not, neuer be at reſt, till you haue gotten it. And ſo I leaue the Appellation, and come to the Declaration, containing in it, Chriſts teaching, then the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whom hetaught.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Spake and ſaid.</hi>] Here are two words vſed to expreſſe his teaching by; they differ not much in ſignification. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of them noteth out, as it were, the opening of his mouth and that he began firſt. The later ſheweth what he vttered when he did ſo open his mouth, and begin to ſpeake. The which to be ſo, we may ſee, not only by the force of the Hebrew word, here vſed in the firſt place, which doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. <hi>in ſermonem prorumpere, vel clamare,</hi> to breake out into words, or to cry; but alſo by the vſe of both the words here vſed, as they are ioyned together elſewhere in the Scriptures: for if we marke them well, wee ſhall finde them ſo taken, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8504:33"/>namely, in <hi>Daniel,</hi> Chapter 3.14.24.26. and Chapter 5.13. and Chapter 6.20. So that here is no myſterie, as I take it, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in this, that two words are vſed, and not one onely. It is to ſhew that Chriſt began to ſpeake firſt, and that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was content to teach his Church A man might iudge, that it was the part of the Church firſt to haue ſpoken to Chriſt, conſidering that hee had beene now abſent from her for a time, and was now come againe in kindnes to viſit her. She ſhould haue called out of the houſevnto him, and haue willed him to come in. But alas, there was too great careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in her; and therefore he is faine to begin with her him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Thus doth God preuent vs with his graces: he comes home to our houſes, and knockes at our doores, and doth call vpon vs alowde, before we will heare him, and let him in. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.20. <hi>I ſtand at the docre, and krocke, if any man heare my voice, and open the doore, I will come in vnto him, and will ſuppe with him, and he with me.</hi> Yea, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes when he doth knocke, we will not ſeeme to heare, and ſo ſuffer him to lay on, knocking ſtill, vntill his head be full of dew, and his lockes with the drops of the night: yea, which is more, after that he hath awakened vs, and we cannot but ſpeake to him, we are loath to ariſe to let him in, making many vaine excuſes for that purpoſe, ſaying (amongſt other things) <hi>I haue put off my coate, how ſhall I put it on? I haue waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my feete, how ſhall I defile them? Cant.</hi> 5.3.</p>
                  <p>Thus I might runne on, to ſhew how backward the Church is on the one ſide, and how forward Chriſt is on the other, to doe her good; but theſe things I will leaue to your owne deeper conſiderations.</p>
                  <p>Here a man may demand, and aske,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                     </label> how Chriſt did ſpeake to his Church: for we findein the Scriptures, that he doth it after ſundrie ſorts, and chiefely foure wayes. Firſt, by his owne voice, and in his owne perſon. Secondly, by the voice of his Spirit. Thirdly, by the voice of an Angell. Laſtly, by the voice of his Miniſter.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt all theſe wayes,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> this laſt doth ſeeme to be the onely way, becauſe that which is here vttered, belongs to the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8504:34"/>Church at all times, and in all ages of the world.</p>
                  <p>Howſoeuer,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> in that Chriſt is ſaid, to ſpeake and ſay, when the Goſpell was deliuered vnto her, wee are taught this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, is there tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching men where his Word is truly taught and deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men. When Wiſedome had ſent forth her maidens they are not ſaid to cry in the higheſt places of the Citie, but ſhee is laid to cry <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.3. When <hi>Noth</hi> ſpake to the old World, and for the ſpace of ſixeſcore yeares together did call vpon them for repentance and amendment of life, that ſo they might not be drowned with the Floud: hee is not ſaid to preach vnto them but Chriſt by his Spirit in him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19.20. Laſtly, when the Apoſtles went vnto the Gentiles, that were a farre off, and ſounded out the words of eternall life vnto them, for their ſaluation: they themſelues are not ſaid to preach to them, but Chriſt himſelfe, euen then, when he was in his owne perſon aſcended vp into heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, and ſate there at the right hand of his Father, in the high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt places, <hi>Ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 2.17. Thus then you ſee, that it is Chriſt, that doth teach men in the Preaching of the Word.</p>
                  <p>And this our Sauiour doth for two cauſes:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> the one is in regard of his office, for hee is the Angell of the Couenant, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1. the Doctor of his Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.8. The Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. the word of God, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.1. and in one word, he is ſent by God to preach, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 61.2. The other is in reſpect of his loue to man, who came into this world to ſaue him, and not to damne him: for he knowes on the one ſide, where no viſion is, there the people periſh, <hi>Prou.</hi> 29.18. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſea</hi> 4.6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.14. And on the other, that none can know his Fathers will without him, vnleſſe he doth rouelle the ſame vnto him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.18.</p>
                  <p>This may teach vs,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> what to iudge of the preaching of Gods word: we muſt not take it for the word of man, but as it is indeed for the word of God. So did the Theſſalonians, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. As for the Miniſter, hee is but the voice, or truncke, whereby Chriſt doth conuev heauenly things vnto vs: in which regard they are compared to Stewards, who muſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8504:34"/>adminiſter, not their owne goods, but their maſters, and one day muſt account for them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. And therefore looke whatſoeuer the Miniſter of Gods word doth deliuer vnto vs out of the word of God, that muſt wee take as proceeding from God; and thinke that God, euen then, doth ſpeake vnto vs himſelfe from heauen, as indeed he doth; according to that in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>For this cauſe muſt we hearken with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, beleeue with ſtedfaſtnes, and practiſe with obedience, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Lord our G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d ſhall make knowne vnto vs.</hi> But now, alas, many doetake that which is ſpoken, as the word of man, and caſt it behinde their backes, as a matter not much to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected: but thoſe that doe ſo, doe deſpiſe God himſelfe, <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k.</hi> 10.16. As this may teach vs what to iudge of preaching of the Word, ſo it may allure our ſoules to come vnto it. For ſhall Chriſt, like a Schoole-maſter, come to teach vs; and ſhall not we, like good ſchollers, draw neere to heare him? If the Kings Maieſtie ſhould ſet vp a ſchoole, and reade Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures vnto men, would not we flocke vnto him, and preſſe vpon him with great companies? But behold here is one greater then the King, that doth come to teach vs: it is the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, euen the very wiſedome of God it ſelfe. And therefore let vs haſten vnto his houſe, and attend at his gates, to heare what he ſhall ſay vnto vs. In the laſt place wee haue here a caueat and a comfort for the Miniſter, in that he is but the voice and mouth of Chriſt, and the Word, that he doth ſpeake, is not his owne. A caueat, that hee doe vtter nothing, but what he is ſure doth come from Chriſt. A comfort, in that he is ſo highly aduanced, as that Chriſt is content to ſpeake vnto men by him and in him Hee is no leſſe honored hereby, then an ambaſſadour is, when hee is made the mouth of his King, <hi>Yea much more honored then he.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to leaue Chriſt teaching, let vs come to the perſon whom he taught. It was his Church. <hi>My welbeloued, ſpake, and ſaid vnto me.</hi> Hee doth direct his words to her, and not to others But why to her? Was ſhee now at this time igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and ſo to be inſtructed? Or was ſhe in trouble, and ſo to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8504:35"/>be comforted? Or was ſhe in a fault, and ſo to be corrected? or was ſhee negligent in her dutie, and ſo to be quickned vp? for which of theſe foure cauſes did he now ſpeake vnto her? for the laſt, as the words following in the text it ſelfe doe ſhew, where ſhe is willed to Ariſe, and to come away. Here I might take an occaſion, in that Chriſt doth thus direct his words vnto her, to ſhew vnto you, that the word of God is a treaſure beſtowed onely vpon the Saints. It is proper to Gods children onely, and not common to the wicked. For howſoeuer the ſound thereof be gone through out the world, and all people haue heard the ſame, according to the letter; yet the ſauing fruit and benefit thereof hath redounded one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them, that are of the houſe-hold of Faith. This I might eaſily confirme vnto you to be true in three reſpects. The firſt is, for the knowledge of it: the ſecond, for the faith of it: and the third for the practiſe of it. For howſoeuer the wicked haue a certaine kinde of knowledge, and a certaine kinde of faith, and a certaine kinde of practiſe: yet they haue neither the ſanctifying knowledge of it, nor the iuſtifying faith of it, nor the vniuerſall practiſe of it. The God of heauen hath kept theſe three as proper and peculiar Iewels for his owne alone.</p>
                  <p>But this point I will paſſe ouer.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> The onely thing, that I will now vrge is this, that the beſt that are, are to be taught and ſchooled in the wayes of their good, as the Church here was by our Sauiour. <hi>Dauid</hi> was a man according to Gods owne heart: yet <hi>Mathan</hi> muſt come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to ſchoole him for his fault, which hee committed with <hi>Vriahs</hi> vvife, as it is in the beginning of the twelfth Chapter of the ſecond booke of <hi>Samuell. Aſa</hi> was a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, King ruling with his good, and remaining faithfull with his Saints: yet <hi>Azariah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Obed</hi> muſt come vnto him, to ſtirre him vp to ſeeke the Lord, as it is in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning alſo of the fifteenth Chapter of the ſecond booke of the <hi>Chronicles. Zerubbabel</hi> vvas a valiant Prince, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious for the honour of his GOD: yet <hi>Haygay</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and <hi>Zachariah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iddo,</hi> muſt come vnto him, to ſet him forward about the building of Gods houſe at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8504:35"/>as it is alſo in the beginning of the fift Chapter of <hi>Ezra.</hi> In a vvord, to pretermit many examples, <hi>Timothie</hi> was a rare youth, being more like an Angell deſcending from heauen, then a man aſcending from the earth (hee did ſo ſpend himſelfe, like a candle, for the good of Gods people:) yet <hi>Paul</hi> muſt vvrite vnto him two Epiſtles, to admoniſh him of his dutie, and to teach him how to behaue himſelfe in the Church, the houſe of God, which is the ground and pillar of truth. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                  <p>The reaſons hereof are three. Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> becauſe they are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in many points and doe not know all thoſe things, that concerne the Lords vvorſhip, and their owne peace. Here we know in part, and here wee Propheſie in part. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9 And howſoeuer <hi>Dakid</hi> was a deepe ſcholler, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more then all his teachers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.99. yet hee was ſo blind in ſome things, that hee was more like a beaſt therein, then a man, as hee doth confeſſe of himſelfe in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.22. when he ſaith, <hi>So fooliſh was I and ignorant: I was a beast be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</hi> Secondly becauſe they are delinquents, and doe not performe all that which they know, but faile exceedingly therein. <hi>In many things</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iames,</hi> Chapter 3.2.) <hi>wee ſinne all.</hi> And although Saint <hi>Paul</hi> were a ſanctified man farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue many others, yet hee bewayleth his owne eſtate in this regard very much, eſpecially, when hee ſaith in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. <hi>I doe not the good thing which I would, but the euill, which I would not, that doe I.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe they are faint-harted, and are ready oftentimes to giue ouer their goodneſſe, chiefely in the time of preſecution. <hi>As for me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2.) <hi>My feete were almoſt gone, my ſteps had wel-neere ſlipt.</hi> And albeit <hi>Ehab</hi> was a rare man, one of 1000. yet in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of his ſoule, hee deſired, that hee might die, and ſaid, <hi>It is now enough, O Lord, take my ſoule, for I am no better then my fathers.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.4. In all theſe reſpects they are to be taught and ſchooled, that ſo they may not erre in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but hold all things, according to the truth; that ſo they may not wander out of the path of righteouſneſſe, but walke ſtill in the ſame; that ſo laſtly they may not faint vnder
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8504:36"/>any croſſe or affliction, but be conſtant therein to their dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayes. So that continuall teaching is neceſſarie for them, in regard of determination in matters of faith, of conuerſation in matters of workes, and of conſolation in matters of triall.</p>
                  <p>The vſe hereof is three-fold:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> the firſt is concerning the Miniſter, the ſecond concerning the people, and the third concerning the Miniſter and the people. The Miniſter is here taught that he muſt neuer leaue off teaching: he muſt preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, and watch thereunto with all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. <hi>My brethren, therefore giue not ener, but labour ſtill time after time, ſo long as you lius; for your congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations will ſtill ſtand in need of teaching.</hi> The people are here ſchoolled, that they muſt neuer giue ouer their ſchoolling; like ſchollers, they muſt to it, day after day, and weeke after weeke, during the terme of their whole liues. For doe they what they can, yet they will be ignorant ſtill, yet they will be faultie ſtill, yet they will be faint-hearted ſtill. And therefore continuall preaching is as needfull for men, as the aire that we breath in, as the clothes that we walke in, as the food that we receiue in, as the houſes that we dwell in, and as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that we liue in. Laſtly, here, both Miniſter and people are inſtructed to attend euermore to inſtruction. The one muſt employ his ſtudie diligently, that he may be able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct other further; and the other muſt frequent the Church carefully, that they themſelues may be inſtructed further.</p>
                  <p>The fruit whereof vnto them both, with their duties, the Apoſtle doth teach, in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. when he ſaith, <hi>Take heed vnto thy ſelfe, and vnto learning: continue therein, for in doing this, thou ſhalt bothſaue thy ſelfe, and them that heare thee. Now vnto him that is able to doe exceeding abundantly aboue all that we aske or thinke, according to the power that worketh in vs, be praiſe in the Church by Ieſus Chriſt, throughout all generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:8504:36"/>
                  <head>THE SECOND SERMON, OF CHRISTIAN LOVE.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Canticles 2. verſe 10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Ariſe, my loue, my faire one, and come thy way.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Mitting the Paraphraſticall expoſition of theſe words; the ſound whereof hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die peirced your eares, you haue nothing now to remember in ſumme (welbeloued in the Lord) but the words which Chriſt did vſe vnto his Church, at what time hee ſpake vnto her, and did behold her thorow the window of his Goſpell. As to day in the fore-noone you hard her words of him; ſo now by Gods grace, you may heare his words to her. In which I commend to your conſiderations two points. The firſt are certaine Appellations; the ſecond certaine Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The appellations are two: the firſt is, <hi>My loue:</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, <hi>My faire one.</hi> The Exhortations are alſo two: the firſt is, <hi>Ariſe:</hi> the ſecond is, <hi>Come away.</hi> The Appellations ſhew how well Chriſt is affected towards his Church. The Exhortations declare, as it were, how well the Church ought to be affected towards Chriſt. The appellations are as argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to moue her. And the Exhortations are as duties mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnto her.</p>
                  <p>But let vs proceed-in order, beginning firſt with the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellations,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8504:37"/>and then comming afterwards vnto the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. The firſt appellation is this, <hi>My loue.</hi> Here you may call to minde, what was obſerued before vpon this word, <hi>My welbeloued,</hi> for both of them are equiualent, and of one force. But yet here is further to be added vnto that: for the loue of Chriſt may be conſidered three wayes. Firſt, it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall towards all his creatures, whereby he loues them all, approuing the ſame to be good, as they proceed from him, and are his creatures, or the workmanſhip of his hands. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as it is ſpeciall towards mankinde, in that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to become a Redeemer for mankinde, after their fall, and not for any other creature, no not for the Angels that fell as well as man. Laſtly, as it is proper to his Elect or cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ones, whereby he accepts of them to life euerlaſting, and hath a purpoſe to doe them good for euermore.</p>
                  <p>Now in this laſt ſenſe is the word here to be taken,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from hence we may ſafely collect this Doctrine, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Sauiour is ſuch an one, as doth loue his Church and people well: they are deare vnto him, they are his dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and his loue; they are ſuch, on whom his heart is ſet. So much doth <hi>Paul</hi> teach vs, when he faith, <hi>And walke in loue, euen as Christ hath loued vs, and hath giuen himſelfe for vs, Epheſ.</hi> 5.2. So much doth <hi>Iohn</hi> teach vs, when hee ſaith. <hi>And from Ieſus Christ, which is a faithfull witneſſe, and the first begotten of the dead, and Prince of the Kings of the earth: vnto him that loued vs, and waſhed vs from our ſins in his blood, Reuel.</hi> 1.5. So much doth <hi>Zachary</hi> teach vs, when hee ſaith, <hi>For he that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of his eye, Zach.</hi> 2.8. So much doth <hi>Zephanie</hi> teach vs, when he ſaith, <hi>Reioyce O daughter Sion, be yee ioyfull, O Iſrael, be glad and reioyce with all thine heart, O daughter Ieruſalem: The Lord thy God in the middeſt of thee is mighti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, he will ſaue, he will quiet himſelfe in his loue, he will reioyce ouer thee with ioy, Zeph.</hi> 3.14.17. So much in one word, doth Chriſt himſelfe teach vs, when he ſaith, <hi>A new conmandement giue I vnto you, that you loue one another, as I haue loued you, that ye alſo loue one another, Iob.</hi> 13.34. Then, as he loued <hi>Iohn</hi> his Diſciple, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.2. and as he loued <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:8504:37"/>his Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. and as hee loued <hi>Lazarus</hi> his friend, together with his two ſiſters <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary, Iohn</hi> 11.5. ſo doth hee loue all thoſe that doe belong vnto him.</p>
                  <p>The reaſons to moue him herevnto are chiefely foure.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> The firſt is, becauſe ſhee is part of himſelfe. <hi>For no man euer yet hated his owne fleſh, but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it, euen as the Lord doth the Church, for we are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones. Eph.</hi> 5.29 30. The ſecond is, becauſe ſhee is like himſelfe, hauing the image of his owne Maieſtie ſtamped in her. As he is holy, ſo ſhee is holy. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.7. For <hi>Simile ſimile gaudet:</hi> like doth reioyce in like, as it is in our prouerbe. The third is, becauſe ſhe doth loue him and hath ſome good care to worſhip and ſerue him. For hee cannot but loue ſuch againe; and that according to his owne word and promiſe, when he ſaith: <hi>He that hath my commandements, and keepeth them, is he that loueth me: and he that loueth me, ſhall be loued of my father; and I will loue him and will ſhew mine owne ſelfe vnto him. Iohn</hi> 14.21. The fourth is, becauſe ſhee is redeemed by him, and it did coſt him much before hee could get her, yea more then ſiluer and gold, euen his owne hart blood, as <hi>Peter</hi> doth well note, in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19. When hee ſaith, <hi>Knowing that you were not redeemed with corruptible things, as ſiluer and gold, from your vaine conuerſation, receiued by the traditions of your fathers, but with the pretious blood of Christ, as of a lambe vndefiled, and without ſpot.</hi> For the more we giue for things, the greater value and price doe we ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the things.</p>
                  <p>But to leaue the reaſons of this doctrine,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> and to come to the vſes of it, this loue that is in Chriſt towards his Church, may ſeruevs well for foure purpoſes. The firſt is, to aſſure vs of glory to come. For it is vnpoſſible, that they ſhould periſh, whom the ſauiour of the world doth loue, and whom hee hath choſen for his vvife. Doubtleſſe nothing ſhall hinder their ſaluation, but all things ſhall worke for there beſt for the accompliſhment thereof. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. Well therefore might our ſauiour ſay of them, as he doth in <hi>Iohn,</hi> Chapter 10.27, 28.29. <hi>My ſheepe here my voyce, and I know them, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8504:38"/>they follow mee, and I giue to them eternall life, and they ſhall neuer periſh, neither ſhall any plucke them out of mine hand: My father which gaue them mee is greater then all, and none is able to take them out of my fathers hand: I and my Father are one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, to open vnto vs our dignitie aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. As <hi>Iohn</hi> did ſay, <hi>behold, what loue the father hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on vs, that wee ſhould be called the ſonnes of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1. So may I ſay, behold what loue the ſonne hath ſhewed on vs, that we ſhould be called the wife of God: for ſo we are in many places of the ſcriptures. Surely there are none in the world aduanced to this degree of honour, but our ſelues, vvho are of the Church. Oh my deare brethren, can vvee conſider enough of this? or can vvee expreſſe it, as it doth deſerue? What? is it true indeede, that the ſonne of God, yea the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne of God, who is the heire apparent of all the world, doth loue vs poore and ſinnefull vvretches, and that hee is well content to marry with vs, and to take vs home to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for his wife? wonderfull! Oh wonderfull! what a thing is this? meditate, Oh meditate, I beſeech you, vpon this point both day and night, and turne it to your good.</p>
                  <p>The third is, to comfort vs againſt the hatred of this world. Here wee ſhall be diſpiſed, and be had in great contempt and diſgrace. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.19. <hi>Math.</hi> 10.22. But as <hi>Elkanah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannah</hi> his wife, <hi>Why weepest thou? and why eatest thou not? and why is thine heart troubled? am not I better to thee then ten ſonnes?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.8. <hi>So may not Christ ſay vnto vs? why are you ſad? or why are you grieued? Is not my loue better to you then the loue of all the world?</hi> Doubtleſſe, Gods children doe finde it ſo to be. Their owne life is not ſo ſweet vnto them, as the loue of Chriſt; according to <hi>Dauids</hi> words, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3. Where, ſpeaking vnto God, he doth ſay, <hi>for thy louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is better then life, therefore my lips ſhall praiſe thee.</hi> But that we may indeede receiue full comfort from hence, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in few words, what manner of loue it is that Chriſt doth beare vnto vs. In it, I commend vnto you foure conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble properties. The firſt is, the greatneſſe of it. The ſecond
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8504:38"/>is, the ſingularitie of it. The third is, the commodity of it. The fourth and laſt is, the perpetuitie of it. For the firſt; it is ſo great that wee cannot by our ſhallow reaches compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it: if all the land vvere paper, and all the vvater vvere incke, and all the plants were pens, and all the creatures were writers, yet they would not, nay, yet they could not expreſſe the greatneſſe of it, as it doth deſerue. For as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth teach vs, the loue of Chriſt paſſeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>Ephoſ.</hi> 3.19. For the ſecond, it is ſo ſingular, that all are not made pertakers of it, but the elect onely: onely the Church is intereſſed in this loue. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25. In this reſpect ſhe is compared to a garden, that is incloſed, to a ſpring that is ſhut vp, and to a fountaine that is ſealed faſt, in <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12. So then, as Chriſt did not pray for the world, but for his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples onely vvhich were in the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.9. So hee loues not the world, but thoſe of his owne which are in the world For the third, it is ſo commodious that to vs it is better then all the world, yea more ſweet and pleaſant vnto vs then any coſtly banquet vvhatſoeuer, made of wine, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pretious things. <hi>Let him kiſſe mee</hi> (ſaith the ſpouſe) <hi>with the kiſſes of his mouth, for thy loue is better then wine. Cant.</hi> 1.1. We need not doubt of this, becauſe without Chriſt we are all but damned perſons, but hauing Chriſt, wee ſhall be ſaued. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16.18. and 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.11.12. But yet remember what the CHVRCH doth ſay: <hi>like the apple tree</hi> (ſaith ſhee) <hi>among the trees of the forreſt, ſo is my welbeloued among the ſonnes of men: vnder his ſhaddow had I delight and ſate downe, and his fruit was ſweet vnto my mouth. Cant.</hi> 2.3. For the fourth and laſt, it is ſo perpetuall, that nothing can breake it off, but it doth continue for euer: well the mountaines may remoue, and the hills may fall downe, but Gods mercy ſhall neuer depart from vs, neither ſhall the couenant of his peace fall away, ſaith the Lord that hath compaſſion on vs. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.10. Thoſe whom Chriſt doth once loue, hee will be ſure to loue to the end. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.1. So that nothing can ſeperate vs from the loue of our God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.39. Now my brethren, ſhall not this comfort vs againſt the hatred of the vvorld?
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8504:39"/>When any doth beginne to deſpiſe vs, let vs cheere vp our hearts with this, that Chriſt doth loue vs. For what are they to Chriſt? Is not his loue better then all their loues? Behold, they are poore, but he is rich: they are weak, but he is ſtrong: they are fooliſh, but he is wiſe: they are baſe, but he is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: in a word, they are mortall, but he is a God immortall. Therefore let not the diſpleaſure of this world daunt vs, but let his fauour euermore comfort vs.</p>
                  <p>The laſt is, to inflame our loues towards him, and to blow the coales thereof, that they may burne out more and more. The loue of Chriſt (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) conſtraineth vs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. And the Church doth tell vs, that Chriſts loue was as a banner ouer her to draw her vnto him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.4. Let it then worke vpon our ſoules, and moue them to affect him. What? ſhall hee loue vs, and ſhall not we loue him againe? What? ſhall he preferre vs before all the world: and ſhall we preferre the world before him? God forbid, as he doth loue vs, ſo let vs loue him againe. Doubtleſſe, if ſome great man ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his loue to a poore woman of the countrey, and be well pleaſed to take her for his wife, we might well thinke her to be diſtracted of her wits, if ſhe ſhould refuſe him, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him againe with the like loue towards him. So after the ſame ſort, may we thinke our ſelues bereft of all our ſenſes, if we loue not the Lord Ieſus, ſeeing he hath loued vs ſo deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Wherefore to end this point, let his loue encreaſe our loue, and knit our hearts the faſter vnto him. Hitherto hath reached the firſt Appellation, the ſecond doth now offer it ſelfe to our examination.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My faire one.</hi>] Here ſeemes to be a wonder, that the Church is faire, who ſaid of her ſelfe, that ſhee was blacke, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4.5. But a greater wonder, that Chriſt ſhould ſay, that ſhe was faire: for man may be deceiued, but Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. Surely man may praiſe one to be faire, when it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo; but Chriſt cannot doe ſo. Man (wee know) may erre in his iudgement, for want of skill and knowledge, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that for faire which is foule, being abuſed by his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in diſcerning formes and complexions; but Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8504:39"/>becauſe in him are hid all the treaſures of knowledge and vnderſtanding, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.3. Man we know may pronounce a falſe ſentence (though he had a true and ſound iudgement) for want of ſight in beholding the partie, either his eyes may be dimme, or elſe the members of the body may be couered and kept from his ſight: but Chriſt cannot, becauſe his eyes are as flames of fire to behold all things moſt clearely, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.14. and all things doe ſtand naked and open before him, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.13. Man (we know) will lie and flatter, ſpeaking of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten contrary to his iudgement and ſight, to curry-fauour with men and women; but Chriſt cannot; becauſe hee is truth it ſelfe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16. He cannot ſpeake diſſemblingly to pleaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but as the very truth is, ſo doth he alwayes ſpeake. Man (wee know) through a fooliſh and beſotted loue, may take one to befaire, which is foule, according to our prouerbe;
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Quiſquis amat ranam, ranam putat eſſe</hi> Diam,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who ſo doth loue the frogge in dike,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He thinkes the ſame</hi> Diana <hi>like.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> So ſtrongly doth affection leade a mans minde to a falſe iudgement; but Chriſt cannot, becauſe he reſpects no mans perſon aboue another, but doth teach the way of the Lord truely, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.16. Finally, man (we know) will extoll and commend a little very highly, and a ſmall beautie in his ſight will ſeeme to be very great: but Chriſt cannot, becauſe he is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.16. Then ſeeing that Chriſt who cannot erre in iudgement, who doth ſee all things moſt plainely, who will flatter no perſon, but ſpeake according to the truth, who through loue cannot mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, but take euery thing as it is, who laſtly doth dwell in glory and Maieſtie vnſpeakeable, doth here praiſe his Spouſe, and commend her fairenes, we may well ſee by it, that her beauty doth excell, and that in pulchritude ſhe is moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
                  <p>From hence then let vs gather this Doctrine,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> that the Church of God is faire and beautifull in the eyes of Chriſt her husband. Large commendations are giuen vnto it in this book often, but I will onely touch a place or two; the firſt ſhal
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8504:40"/>be out of the firſt Chapter, the other out of the fourth. In the firſt chapter and fourteenth verſe, we find theſe words ſpoken by our Sauiour vnto his Spouſe, <hi>My loue, behold, thou art faire, behold thou art faire, thine eyes are like the doues.</hi> And in the fourth chapter and ſeauenth verſe, he doth ſpeake thus vnto her, <hi>Thou art all faire, my loue, and there is no ſpot in thee. Dauid</hi> alſo ſpeaking of her in the 45. Pſalme, verſ. 13.14. doth break out into theſe words, and ſay, <hi>The Kings daughter is all glorious within, her clothing is of broydred gold, ſhee ſhall be brought vnto the King in raiment of needle-worke.</hi> And whereas the Saints of God, that ſtand on Mount Sion with Ieſus Chriſt the Lambe, and haue his Fathers name written in their foreheads, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed out at large vnto vs in the fourteenth chapter of the <hi>Reuelations,</hi> and the beginning thereof. Amongſt other things there aſcribed vnto them, this is one, <hi>That in their mouthes there is found no guile, and that they are without ſpot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of God,</hi> verſ. 5. In a word, it is ſaid, in <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.8. that there is granted vnto the wife of Chriſt, <hi>That ſhe ſhould be arrayed with pure fine linnen, and ſhining, and that this fine linnen is the righteouſneſſe of Saints.</hi> Thus in few words it is apparent that the Church is faire and beautifull in the eyes of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Not,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> that ſhe glittereth with outward and ſenſible beautie, which as it is remoued from the roote of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> that had no forme in it to be deſired, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.2. ſo are his branches and members burnt and ſwootie, as if they had lien among the pots, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.13. but this her beauty is inward, and according to that which is in the heauens aboue, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13. It ſtandeth not in a faire white skinne, or in a goodly complexion, and well made body, nor yet in gorgeous garments, or rich exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ornaments, whether the ſame doe reſpect the bodie of man, or the outward worſhip of the Lord; but it ſtandeth in the glorious and glittering robes of Ieſus Chriſt, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, which we call <hi>Iustification,</hi> and in the precious and moſt ſhining ornaments of the holy Spirit, and his graces, which we terme <hi>Sanctification.</hi> Doubtleſſe our Sauiour doth not looke vpon the Church as ſhee is in her ſelfe by nature, and as ſhe is polluted by many ſins and tranſgreſſions: but he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8504:40"/>doth behold her, as ſhe is iuſtified in himſelfe (hauing all her iniqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es done away through his death and paſſion and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding moſt iuſt and vpright in the ſight of God his Father, through the imputation of his righteouſneſſe and obedience) and as ſhe is ſanctified already in part, by the working of the Spirit through the Word and Sacraments, and ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in whole, when ſhe is receiued vp into the heauens, and there really married vnto him in all ioy and felicitie for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. For as a man who doth loue his Bride well, doth not fixe his eyes vpon her blemiſhes, and defaults, but doth ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looke them, and behold onely her comely parts, her paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, her friends, her beautie, her wiſdome, her modeſtie her dowrie, her rich ornaments, and ſuch things alone, as may commend her, and make her to be gratious in his eyes; ſo deales here our Sauiour leſus Chriſt: though his Spouſe haue many imperfections and blemiſhes about her, yet he doth ſet none of them in the ſight of his countenance, but caſting his eyes, as it were, ouer and beſides them, he doth onely behold ſuch things in her, as are moſt comely and excellent. He doth ſee how ſhe is borne againe, and made a new creature by the working of his holy Spirit. Hee doth ſee, how ſhee is clenſed from all her ſins by his blood and bitter paſſion. He doth ſee how ſhe is clothed with his righteouſnes, and with that perfect obedience which he yeelded vnto his Father in all the points of his law. He doth ſee how ſhe is re-created and made againe, in ſome part, according to his owne Image, in vnderſtanding and holines, in faith, hope, loue, feare, humility, patience, know ledge, and many other graces abounding in her more and more. Finally, he doth ſee, how ſhee ſhall be decked with all graces hereafter, and be beautified with all rich ornaments whatſoeuer, euen in the end of the world, when all imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall be taken away from her, and ſhe ſhall be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in euery reſpect and conſideration. And for this cauſe doth he here commend her beauty, and ſay, that <hi>ſhe is faire.</hi> So that this is in a double regard, the one is of Iuſtification, which ſhe hath from him; and the other is of Sanctification, which ſhe hath from his Spirit: for by him ſhe is iuſtified, and by his Spirit ſhee is ſanctified, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. Wherefore then, wee are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8504:41"/>made faire two waies. The firſt is by the imputation of Chriſts moſt excellent forme vnto vs. The ſecond is by a reall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of his louely graces into vs: for he doth both clenſe vs from our ſinnes, and alſo cloth vs with the ſilken robes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>The knowledge of this Doctrine is profitable vnto vs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> firſt, for Conſolation: ſecondly, for Exhortation, and thirdly, for Confutation. For Conſolation, becauſe we may from hence receiue ſome comfort, in that we are faire in his eyes, who is able to ſaue vs. It is the whole deſire of the Church to be comely and handſome in the eyes of Chriſt If he accept of her, and think her faire, it is all well, what can ſhe deſire more? A ſingular ioy it muſt needs then be vnto her to vnderſtand for certaine, that ſhe is trim and beautifull indeed in his ſight. And therefore Chriſt, as it were, to cheare her vp, doth pronounce, in manner as you haue heard, that <hi>ſhee is faire.</hi> We may reioyce and triumph in this, euen ſo many as vnfainedly doe loue him, that we are ſo comely and pleaſing in his eyes. The Diuell, as he hath in one hand the glaſſe of <hi>Selfe-loue,</hi> to ſet before men, to draw them on to their ſinnes, that ſo they therunto looking, may <hi>Narciſſus</hi>-like, berauiſhed with their owne beauty: ſo hee hath in the other hand, the glaſſe of <hi>Gods-law,</hi> to preſent vnto them, to terrifie them for their ſins, that ſo they beholding themſelues therein, may <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>-like, goe and hang themſelues. But againſt this his poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we haue here a good Antidote, if he cry out and ſay, <hi>Thou art a deformed perſon, thou art foule and filthy, thy ſins are many and grieuous, the Lord of glory cannot regard thee,</hi> &amp;c. Doe thou reply this anſwere backe againe vnto him, and ſay, <hi>Auoid Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, auoid thou lyer; it is not true which thou doeſt ſay, I am faire and beautifull, and the God of heauen doth respect me. I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue him, that here ſpeaketh, who is truth it ſelfe; but I will not beleeue thee, who haſt beene a murtherer and a layer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, Ioh.</hi> 8.44. Wherefore my brethren, comfort your ſelues with theſe things: for looke what Chriſt doth here ſpeake to the whole Church, the ſame hee ſpeaketh to euery faithful perſon in the Church. Is there faith, repentance, loue, feare, zeale, humility, and a care of true godlines within thee?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8504:41"/>then paſſe not for any temptation of Satan: for although there be the remnants of ſin abiding ſtill in thee, and a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of diuers infirmities with thy heauenly graces; yet this is not taken away from thee, <hi>My loue, my faire one:</hi> for Chriſt doth behold thy vertues, and comely ornaments, wherewith thou art decked, and he doth not ſtand gazing vpon thy ſins and deformities, wherewith thou art polluted: he is content, as it were, to ouer-looke them, and to paſſe them ouer, as if they were not, and that as it may ſeeme for theſe cauſes. Firſt, becauſe they are already done away from thee by his merit and death, when he died for thee. Secondly, becauſe they are ouer-reached, and out-valued by his graces and gifts in thee, which doe far ſurmount them all. Thirdly, and laſtly, becauſe he will wholly purge thee from them in the end, when he ſhal take thee out of this world, and make thee ſit with him in the higheſt heauens. In regard whereof, our Sauiour doth iudge thee to be neuer a whit, as it were, the leſſe beautifull and faire in his eyes, for thy tranſgreſſions, then if thou hadſt none at all: euen as a Bride-groome with vs, doth thinke his Bride to be nothing the leſſe comely or handſome for a little dirt that is vpon her, which is not naturall and continuall, but acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and vaniſhing, as who hath contracted the ſame vnto her ſelfe by her labour and paines, about ſome foule and filthie worke, and may eaſily alſo waſh the ſame away from her with water at any time, when ſhe will. Wherefore finde out thoſe graces of Sanctification, which I nominated euen now, and though they be not perfect or full within thee, yet be ſure they be in truth and ſincerity, and doubt not, but that thou art moſt faire and beautifull in the ſight of the euer-liuing God, prate the diuel, or the world, neuer ſo much to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>For Exhortation, becauſe we may from hence be ſtirred vp to vſe all poſſible meanes, to get ſome holines and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes vnto our ſelues, that as the Church is faire, ſo we our ſelues alſo may be faire. Surely, vnleſſe that we be pure be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, be patient, be louing, be humble, be faithfull, be iuſt; in one word, be deuout and religious; we cannot, nay, we may not perſwade our ſelues, that wee are of the Church. In the Church indeed we may be, but of the Church we cannot be:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8504:42"/>for that is a company of Saints, or holy ones alone. They are, as <hi>Peter</hi> doth ſpeake of them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>A choſen Generation, a royall Prtesthood, an holy Nation, and a peculiar people, to ſhew forth the vertues of him that hath called them out of darknes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his marueilous light.</hi> If wee reade ouer the holy Scriptures, wee ſhall neuer finde, that any doe belong to Chriſt, who are not holy and righteous like to Chriſt. <hi>They that are Christs</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Galath.</hi> 5.24.) <hi>haue crucified the fleſh, with the affections and the lusts.</hi> Againe, <hi>If any man be in Christ</hi> (ſaith he, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.) <hi>let him be a new creature. Old things are paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, behold, all things are become new. In this</hi> (ſaith Saith <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.10.) <hi>are the children of God knowne, and the children of the Diuell: whoſoeuer doth not righteouſnes, is not of God, neither he that loueth not his brother.</hi> Likewiſe, he ſaith, verſ. 3. <hi>And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man that hath this hope in him, purgeth himſelfe, euen as he is pure.</hi> Wherfore, my brethren, let this awaken vs vp, that we may be from hence-forward vpright and innocent perſons, as we ought to be, hauing both the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt vpon vs, and the holines of the ſpirit within vs. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, when our Sauiour did firſt caſt a loue vnto vs, we were as loathſome and vgly creatures, and lay wallowing in our blood, <hi>Ez.</hi> 16.6. yet now ſince he is content to take vs for his owne, let vs not lie any longer in our filthines, but waſh our ſelues in his blood, and bathe our ſoules in the water of his Spirit. In this regard we muſt be like <hi>Rebecca,</hi> when ſhe was brought to <hi>Iſaak</hi> for a wife: and vnto the Virgins at <hi>Suſhan,</hi> when the King <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> was to goe in vnto them. We muſt be altered and changed cleane from that wee were in former times. We muſt now haue our hands adorned with the brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets of good and charitable workes vnto our brethren. Wee muſt now haue our eares hanged with the earings of faith and obedience to Gods word. We muſt now haue our neckes beautified with the golden chaine of Chriſtian vertues. In a word, we our ſelues muſt now be wholly perfumed with the ſweet ointments, and pleaſant odors of Ieſus Chriſt, and of his Spirit; elſe how ſhall wee perſwade our ſelues, that wee are of the number of the Church, when we our ſelues are not faire, like vnto the Church.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:8504:42"/>
                  <p>For confutation, becauſe we may from hence haue ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent matter, to confute not onely thoſe, who are foule and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in their wayes, to be no wife at all vnto Chriſt, but alſo thoſe that hold vs to be ſo loathſome vnto God, that we may not goe vnto him immediately our ſelues in our prayers and ſupplications, but muſt vſe certaine mediators and interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, who may pray vnto him for vs, and obtaine that of him that we ſue vnto him for. For ſurely, ſeeing we are precious in the ſight of Chriſt, and faire in his eies, there is no doubt at all to be made, but that we may with boldnes and confidence of heart come before him in our owne perſons, with all our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſupplications, to craue of him whatſoeuer is according to his will, either reſpecting his glory, or the ſaluation of our ſoules. For this vſe doth he himſelfe make of this Doctrine, as we may ſee, by <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. when he doth vſe theſe words vnto his Church, ſaying, <hi>My done, that art in the holes of the rocke, in the ſecret places of the ſtaires, ſhew me thy ſight, let me heare thy voice, for thy voice is ſweet, and thy ſight comely.</hi> He perſwades her to come vnto him by this reaſon or argument, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee is faire and comely in his ſight. So that our pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chritude or beautie ſhould allure vs vnto him. But let vs heare what Rome doth ſay to the contrary. As a meane and ſilly ſubiect (ſaith ſhe) is vnworthy to come in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with his ſuits vnto his King or Prince, and therefore muſt vſe ſome Courtiers or perſons of eſtate to be ſpokeſ-men for him, and to commend his ſuite vnto his King or Prince, that ſo he may the ſooner obtaine it. So man, through his ſins and corruptions, is altogether vnworthy, to preſent himſelfe in his owne perſon, before Ieſus Chriſt the King of Kings, and the Prince of Princes; and therefore in all ſubmiſſion he muſt vſe the mediation either of Saints or Angels, when he is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence any ſuite vnto him, if he purpoſe to ſpeed therein, and to haue the ſame granted vnto him. For this cauſe ſhe iumps right with the Heathen people of old, and the graceleſſe nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world. For as they conſtituted and made ſeuerall gods, or goddeſſes, for ſeuerall nations, for ſeuerall times, for ſeuerall creatures, and for the ſeuerall parts of mans body: ſo doth ſhe ſubordinate and appoint for all theſe, ſeuerall Saints
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8504:43"/>or Angels: as for example they had <hi>Neptune</hi> for Troy, <hi>Venus</hi> for Cyprus, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nerua</hi> for Athens, <hi>Iuno</hi> for Carthage, and <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> for Rome: ſo ſhe hath S. <hi>George</hi> for England, S. <hi>Andrew</hi> for Scotland, S. <hi>Patricke</hi> for Ireland, S. <hi>Dennis</hi> for France, S. <hi>Iames</hi> for Spaine, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> for Rome. They pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Bellona</hi> in the time of warre, to <hi>Ceres</hi> in the time of ſcarcity, to <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> in the time of ſicknes, to <hi>Liber</hi> in the time of captiuity, to <hi>Bacchus</hi> in the time of hunger, to <hi>Neptune</hi> in the time of tempeſts, &amp; to <hi>Iuno</hi> in the time of child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. So ſhe prayeth to S. <hi>George</hi> in the time of war, to S. <hi>Anne</hi> in the time of pouerty, to S. <hi>Roch</hi> in the time of ſickenes, to S. <hi>Leonard</hi> in the time of captiuity, to S. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbane</hi> in the time of hunger, to S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> in the time of tempeſts, and to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> in the time of child-bed. They conſecrated the Swan vnto <hi>Apollo,</hi> the Peacock to <hi>Iuno,</hi> the Doue vnto <hi>Venus,</hi> the Night-crow vnto <hi>Minerua,</hi> the Dogge vnto <hi>Mars,</hi> the Honey vnto <hi>Mercury,</hi> the Wheat vnto <hi>Ceres,</hi> &amp; the roſe vnto <hi>Cupid.</hi> So ſhe hath conſecrated her Sheepe vnto <hi>Vandolius,</hi> her Horſes vnto <hi>Eulogius,</hi> her Oxen to <hi>Luke,</hi> her Purſe to <hi>Sythe,</hi> and her Pigges to <hi>Anthony.</hi> Finally, they allotted to <hi>Minerua</hi> the head, to <hi>Iuno</hi> the heart, to <hi>Mars</hi> the breaſt, to <hi>Iupiter</hi> the ſpirit, to <hi>Mercury</hi> the tongue, to <hi>Bacchus</hi> the throat, to <hi>Hercules</hi> the armes, to <hi>Cupid</hi> the liuer, to <hi>Apollo</hi> the palmes, and to <hi>Venus</hi> the ſecrets. So ſhe hath allotted to <hi>Anastatius</hi> her head, to <hi>Otilia</hi> her eyes, to <hi>Apollonia</hi> her teeth, to <hi>Blaze</hi> her necke, and to <hi>Eraſmus</hi> her belly. Of theſe things we may reade a little in the booke of Martyrs, where theſe verſes amongſt many others, are compoſed and ſet downe for our inſtruction.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To Saint</hi> Sythe <hi>for my purſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Saint</hi> Loy, <hi>ſaue mine horſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For my teeth to Saint</hi> Apoline,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To Saint</hi> Iob <hi>for the Poxe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Saint</hi> Luke <hi>ſaue mine Oxe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Saint</hi> Anthonie <hi>ſaue my ſwine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To Maiſter</hi> Iohn Shorne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That bleſſed man borne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For the ague to him we apply.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:8504:43"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which iugleth with a boote,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I beſhrow his heart roote.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That will truſt him, and it be I.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such was our truſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such was our luſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vpon creatures to call and cry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As men did pleaſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For euery diſeaſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To haue a god peculiarly.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But what ſhall wee doe vvith this rabble and vnknowne reute of Saints? we need them not. For we our ſelues may goe boldly vnto Ieſus Chriſt without their mediation or others: for he doth well accept of vs, and we are faire and beautifull in his eyes, yea, hee doth take great delight and pleaſure in our preſence and company, as it is intimated by the ſpirit of God in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.8. vvhere it is ſaid, that the Saints of God doe make him glad, while he is in the Iuory pallaces with them. Let vs therefore goe vnto him in our owne perſons, and not truſt vnto the mediation of others, whether they be Saints or Angels. And as for this ſimilitude, which the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Rome doth alledge, deriued from an earthly King and his manner of dealing with his ſubiects, <hi>viz. poſſe nos per iſtos are ad deum, ſicut per comites peruenitur ad regem,</hi> that men by ſuch mediators may goe to God, as they goe to Kings by thoſe who are honourable in their courts. I anſwere with Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who did obuiate the ſame obiection in his time, <hi>hoc eſt miſeravti excuſatione,</hi> that this is to pretend a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excuſe. For there is no good fitneſſe or agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt it, and that, for the which it is produced, neither in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Chriſt himſelfe, nor of his Saints and Angels.</p>
                  <p>Not of Chriſt himſelfe, becauſe there are theſe differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces betwixt him, and an earthly King. Firſt, he can heare all ſuites and ſupplications, which may be put vp vnto him: but an earthly King cannot, becauſe his buſineſſe will not afford him ſo much time. Secondly, hee can be in no danger of ſickneſſe or deſtruction, by the admittance of any perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his preſence: but an earthly King may, becauſe his body is ſubict to diſeaſes and death as well as others, which diſeaſes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8504:44"/>and death may eaſily be brought vpon him by contagious and treacherous perſons, if once they may haue their free acceſſe vnto him vvhen they vvill. Laſtly, hee cannot be deceiued by the falſe informations of ſuch ſuppliants, as doe come vnto him, as who doth behold all things, and ſee the very ſecrets of the hart within, but an earthly King may, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe oftentimes both the perſons themſelues, and alſo their ſuites are vnknowne vnto him.</p>
                  <p>Not of his Saints or Angels, becauſe there are theſe diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements betwixt them and worldly courtiers. Firſt, they cannot heare vs when we ſpeake vnto them, nor vnderſtand what wee ſay in our praiers before them (for that is a thing proper and peculiar to God alone to heare them that are farre abſent from him, and to vnderſtand what is in their harts and ſoules within:) but worldly courtiers may heare and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe ſupplications, which are brought vnto them, becauſe they are ſet downe in plaine termes and words before their eyes. Secondly, as they haue acceſſe vnto Ieſus Chriſt, ſo the reſt of the Saints haue vvhich are liuing vpon the earth, for the throne of grace is open as well for theſe as for them. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. and Chapter 10.19.20. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.18. but vvorldly courtiers may come in boldly vnto their King, when others are ſhut out, becauſe their faithfulnes is knowne, and they haue ſome ſeruice to doe about his Maieſtie. Finally, as they haue grace and fauour in the ſight of Chriſt for the procurement of any benefit or good turne, ſo all the reall members of his body haue alſo, vvhich are here warring vpon the earth: for hee is no accepter of perſons. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34 35. and <hi>Math.</hi> 7.7. But worldly courtiers are ſo grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with their Kings, that they haue almoſt what they will aske, when other ſilly ſubiects and baſe wretches are ſent emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty away and can obtaine little or nothing at all. So that then this compariſon or ſimilitude, is ſaples and not worth a ruſh, and therefore let no wiſe man be moued by it.</p>
                  <p>Hauing thus gone ouer the Appellations, let vs now ſtand a little vpon the Exhortations. They are in number two, as I told you before. The firſt is, <hi>Ariſe,</hi> the ſecond is, <hi>come away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ariſe.]</hi> The Church at this time was in ſome drowſie ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8504:44"/>and much oppreſſed with a ſpirituall lazineſſe, that made her vnwilling to walke a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter Chriſt her husband, in the waves of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. Howſoeuer he came ſo neere her, as to looke through his Goſpell vpon her; yet ſhee ſate ſtill, and moued not ſo much as one foot, to come vnto him; ſuch frailty and imperfection was in her: Either ſhe lay ſnorting in the pleaſures of this preſent world; or ſhee was preſſed downe and tired with that heauy burthen of originall corruption ſpoken of in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.1. or ſhe was terrified with outward perſecution, and ſo, after the example of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, fled as it were, from Chriſt, and hid her ſelfe in ſome cabbin or hole, not daring to peepe out of the ſame. But howſoeuer it came to paſſe, whether this way or that way, it is certaine, that ſhe was in ſome fault, and is here called vpon to amend it: for to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe,</hi> is nothing els, but to leaue ſin, and to walke in righteouſnes; as wee may ſee by the Apoſtles words, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.34. when hee ſaith, <hi>Awake to liue righteouſly, and ſin not:</hi> ſo that to liue righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and not to ſinne any more, is to <hi>Awake,</hi> or to <hi>Ariſe.</hi> Here in that Chriſt doth thus ſpeake vnto his Church, and will her to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, I might note vnto you, firſt, that the beſt of al are moſt fraile and full of imperfections: then that they are to be ſtirred vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their duties and to be whetted on by the words of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for ſurely they are like vnto greene wood, that muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies blowne; vnto dull horſes, that muſt be alwaies ſpurd; vnto blunt kniues, that muſt be alwaies whet; and vnto lame beaſts, that muſt be alwaies driuen. But theſe things I will paſſe ouer, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the meditation thereof vnto your ſelues.</p>
                  <p>The principall matter that I now will ſtand vpon, is this:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> That men muſt not continue in their ſinnes, but ariſe from them, and leaue them. So <hi>Eſay</hi> doth teach vs, ſaying, <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane, take away the euill of your workes from before mine eyes, ceaſe to doe euill, learne to doe well, Eſay</hi> 1.16.17. So <hi>Ezechiel</hi> doth teach vs, ſaying, <hi>Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſſions, whereby you haue tranſgreſſed, and make you a new heart, and a new ſpirit, for why will you die, O houſe of Iſrael? Ezec.</hi> 18.31. So <hi>Daniel</hi> doth teach vs, ſaying, <hi>Wherefore, O King, let my counſel be acceptable vnto thee, and breake off thy ſin by righteouſnes, and thine iniquity by mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poore; loe, let there be an healing of thine error, Dan.</hi> 4.24. So <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt doth teach vs, ſaying, <hi>Repent, for the kingdome
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8504:45"/>of heauen is at hand: O generation of Vipers, who hath forewarned you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ye from the anger to come? bring forth therefore fruits worthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, and thinke not to ſay with your ſelues, we haue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham to our father, Mat.</hi> 3.2.7.8.9. So Chriſt doth teach vs. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Behold, thou art made whole, ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee, Ioh.</hi> 5.14. So <hi>Peter</hi> doth teach vs, ſaying, <hi>Amend your li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and be baptiſed euery one of you in the name of Ieſus Christ, for the remiſſion of ſins, and ye ſhall receiue the gift of the holy Ghoſt, Act.</hi> 2.38. So in a word, <hi>Paul</hi> doth teach vs, ſaying, <hi>Awake thou that ſteepeſt, and ſtand vp from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light, Epheſ</hi> 5.14.</p>
                  <p>The reaſons why we muſt leaue our ſins,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> and not continue in them, are chiefely foure. Firſt, becauſe they doe anger God, whom we ſhould pleaſe in all things, and much offend his Maieſty. When <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> failed in their duties, and committed, in mans iudgment, but a ſmall fault, at the Waters of <hi>Meribah,</hi> when they did not ſanctifie the Lord in the preſence of the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, as they ſhould haue done; the Lord was ſo offended with them for it, that hee would not giue them leaue, and ſo let them liue to bring their people into the land of Canaan, which he had giuen vnto them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.12 Secondly, becauſe they doe wound our ſoules and conſciences, troubling them, as grauell doth our feet within our ſhooes, as we may ſee by the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of his miſerable eſtate, in this regard, in the beginning almoſt of the 32. Pſalme, and making his petition vnto the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty for the redreſſe thereof, in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 51.8. when he ſaith, <hi>Make me to heare ioy and gladnes, that the bones which thou haſt broken may reioyce.</hi> And againe, in verſ. 12. <hi>Reſtore to me the ioy of thy ſaluation, and ſtabliſh me with thy free Spirit.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe they hinder good things from vs, and are as a wall betweene God and vs, to ſtop his benefits from comming downe vpon vs, <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.1.2. <hi>Your iniquiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> (ſaith <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5.25.) <hi>haue turned away theſe things, and your ſins haue hindred good things from you.</hi> Laſtly, becauſe they wil bring deſtruction to vs at the laſt, and caſt vs downe into hel; vnleſſe, to wit, we doe leaue them in time: for ſo much doth Chriſt teach vs in <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3. when he ſaith, <hi>But, except you amend your liues, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh:</hi> ſo doth the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. in theſe words, <hi>For if yee liue after the fleſh, yee ſhall die,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8504:45"/>but if ye mortifie the deeds of the body by the ſpirit, yee ſhall liue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This ſerues firſt to reproue them,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> who continue ſtill in thier ſins, and by no means will leaue their tranſgreſſions: of them the world is too full: wee finde by experience that nothing can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime the greater ſort from their looſe and licentious wayes, chiefly in this braſen and iron age wherin we liue: for neither the Preachers of God in exhorting, nor the goodnes of God in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling nor the will of God in commanding, nor the Spirit of God in mouing, nor the benefits of God in bleſſing, nor the iudgments of God in puniſhing, can preuaile with many of vs to turne vs to the Lord, or cauſe vs to ariſe out of the warme bed of our carnall delights. So that the Lord may iuſtly make his complaint of vs, as he did of Iſrael, ſaying, <hi>I harkened and heard, but none ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, no man repented him of his wickednes ſaying, what haue I done? euery man turned to their race, as the horſe ruſheth into the battell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This ſerues ſecondly to comfort ſuch, as haue forſaken their ſins and haue caſt away their iniquities: though the world doth ſcorne them, becauſe they will not runne to the ſame exceſſe of riot with them, as they did heretofore: yet here is a comfort for them; they doe but their dutie and that which the ſcorners themſelues ought to doe.</p>
                  <p>This ſerues thirdly, to ſtirre vs and to rouſe vs vp out of the bed of our ſecurity. We muſt not lie ſtill in the ſame, like the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, who is vnwilling to ariſe out of his ſleepe, ſaying, <hi>yet a little ſleepe, a little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands together, Prou.</hi> 6.10. But we muſt leaue our ſins with ſpeed, and forſake them. And therefore, my brethren, conſider with your ſelues, in what ſinnes you are aſleepe; whether it be in the ſin of ignorance, or in the ſin of infidelity, or in the ſin of pride, or in the ſinne of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or in the ſin of drunkennes, or in the ſin of whoredome, or in the ſin of ſwearing, or in the ſin of lying, or in the ſin of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or in the ſin of malice, or in one word, in the ſin of any breach of Gods Commandements; whatſoeuer it be forſake it and leaue it. I come now, as a <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> to requeſt this at your hands, and as a <hi>Ionah</hi> to Niniueh, to proclaime warre againſt you, vnleſſe you doe it. Oh, remember (I beſeech you) the reaſons before going and let them ſinke into your hearts for your good. Ariſe firſt, and leaue all your ſins, that you may not anger your
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8504:46"/>God any further, but bring good contentment vnto him in all your waies, as the children of the liuing God ought to doe. But if you care not for Gods diſpleaſure, yet ariſe in the ſecond place and leaue all your ſins, that you may not wound your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and be, as it were, hangmen vnto your ſelues, to teare your owne fleſh with your owne nailes, but that you may reioyce and be glad all the dayes of your liues. But if your conſciences be dead, and as it were ſeared with an hot iron to feele nothing, ſo that no ſin doth trouble it: yet ariſe in the third place, and leaue all your ſins, that you may not impoueriſh your owne perſons, and bring your ſelues and your poſterity to meere beggery, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in regard of the ſoule and the good eſtate thereof, but that you may receiue plentifull bleſſings from the Lord, and be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with his benefits both temporall and eternall, appertaining either to ſoule or body.</p>
                  <p>But if laſtly, you care not much for the bleſſings and benefits of God, as hauing enough already, and thinking your ſelues ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently happy without him, yet ariſe and leaue all your ſins, that you may not be damned in hell for euer, and there lie tormented in flames of fire that cannot be quenched, but that you may be ſaued, and come to life euerlaſting, where you may reioyce in ioyes that are vnſpeakeable. I hope, that theſe things will awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken you, and bring you home vnto your God: and ſo I come vnto the laſt branch of my Text, which is, <hi>Come away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come away.]</hi> Becauſe it is better to lie ſtill, then to ariſe and goe aſtray: our Sauiour ſhewing vs how wee ſhould moue, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs not onely to ariſe, but addeth further, that we muſt come away, <hi>to wit,</hi> after him, leauing this world, and all the things therein behinde vs. As the firſt Exhortation was needfull, ſo is this latter: For the Church was now vnwilling to ſtirre after Chriſt. In this caſe ſhe was like a ſilly woman, who in the Winter would faine liue at home, and in no caſe take a iourney abroad, as knowing that time of the yeare to be vnſeaſonable for her tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling: and that, firſt, becauſe the dayes are ſhort: ſecondly, becauſe the aire is cold: thirdly, becauſe the wayes are foule: fourthly, becauſe the Element is watrie and full of raine: fiftly, becauſe the proſpect of the country is doleful: and laſtly, becauſe the danger for her body and goods is great. The words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8504:46"/>doe ſhew that this was her eſtate, wherein Chriſt doth tell her, that the Winter was now paſt, and the Spring come, and therefore ſhe was to Ariſe and to come away.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, from hence let vs collect this Doctrine,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> that it is the part of all good Chriſtians, to leaue this world, and to goe after Chriſt. The Church doth promiſe to doe the ſame, <hi>Draw me,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>and we will runne after thee, Cant.</hi> 1.3. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in act and deed did performe the like, <hi>They left all, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Christ, Matth.</hi> 19.27. The ſame is reported of the ſheepe of Chriſt: <hi>My ſheepe</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>heare my voice, and I know them, and they follow me, Ioh.</hi> 10.27. We finde alſo the like in that hundreth fortie and foure thouſand, that ſtood with the Lambe on Mount Sion, and had his Fathers name written in their foreheads: for this commendation is giuen of them; <hi>Theſe are they, which are not defiled with women, for they are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins; theſe follow the Lambe whitherſoeuer he goeth: theſe are bought from men, being the first fruits vnto God, and to the Lambe, Reu.</hi> 14.4. Thus you ſee how we ſhould goe after Chriſt, and be well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leaue all the world, to follow him.</p>
                  <p>The reaſons to moue vs herevnto are theſe. Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> becauſe he is our husband, and we are his wife. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. For the wife muſt follow her husband, and forſaking all other friends muſt cleaue onely vnto him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.25. Secondly, becauſe he will then take a great delight in vs, and ſatisfie himſelfe in our loue, according to that which is in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11.12. where it is ſaid, <hi>Hearken (O daughter) and conſider, &amp; encline thine eare: forget alſo thine owne people, &amp; thy fathers houſe. So ſhal the King haue pleaſure in thy bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: for hee is thy Lord, and reuerence thou him.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe wee are dead to the world, and a liue in him. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l.</hi> 3.3.4. Laſtly, becauſe he will liberally reward all ſuch as doe come after him. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſay vnto you: that when the ſonne of man ſhall ſit in the throne of his Maiestie, ye which followed me in the regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall ſit alſo vpon twelue thrones, and iudge the twelue tribes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. And whoſoeuer ſhall forſake houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my names ſake, he ſhall receiue an hundred-fold more, and ſhall inherit euerlaſting life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This reproues thoſe, that care not for Chriſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> but followes this world altogither. Whatſoeuer they be, whether rich or poor,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8504:47"/>high or low, wiſe or vnwiſe, bond or free, male or female, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that they are none of Chriſts. Hee will diſclaime them, and not approue them for his owne. <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>come to mee, and hate not his father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brethren, and ſiſters: yea, and his owne life alſo, he cannot be my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. And whoſoeuer beareth not his croſſe, and commeth after mee, cannot be my Diſciple. Luk.</hi> 14.26.27. wherefore let this worke repentance in the harts of worldly men, and turne them to the louing Lord.</p>
                  <p>As this doth ſerue to reproue all ſuch as preferre the world before Chriſt: ſo it may ſerue alſo to prouoke vs all, to preferre Chriſt before the world. Surely it ſhould moue vs, to ſet him ſtill before vs, and pricke vs forward to goe after him: if a man were in a farre country farre from his friends and neereſt kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, though his eyes did behold the faireſt pictures, his eares heare the ſweeteſt muſicke, his mouth taſt the daintieſt meate, his body lie vpon the ſofteſt bed, and all his ſenſes compaſſed about with the rareſt obiects of tenne thouſand: yet would his heart be at home, vnleſſe hee were bewitched, as the poets faine of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes,</hi> whom the cups of <hi>Circe</hi> did make to forget his natiue country and faithfull wife. So, cuen ſo, vnleſſe we be inchanted with the witchcraft of the deuill, all the traſh and pelfe of this world cannot hold vs here below, but our harts will mount vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and be fixed vpon our Bride-grome, in whoſe preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: and all our trauell will eſpecially tend to attaine vnto our country in the heauens, and to celeſtiall Ieruſalem that is aboue. For wee are here as ſtrangers and pilgrimes vpon the earth. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. and our <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or corporation, whereof wee are members, is in the heauen, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. Surely our earthly houſes are not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, rather an Inne to lodge in, then a permanent manſion to abide in. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. wherefore, I pray you, let vs euermore ſet our hearts vpon Chriſt, and follow him. It is recorded in the greeke and Romaine ſtories, that <hi>Hyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicrataea</hi> did ſo excedingly loue her busband <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>hridates</hi> King of Pontus, that when hee was put to flight, and enforced to wander vp and downe the woodes and deſerts to ſaue his life, ſhe attyred in mans apparrell did follow him euery way through th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8504:47"/>thinne, reputing her kingdome, her wealth, her country, and her happineſſe to be there where her husband was. So after the ſame manner, if we be ſo faithfully affected to our moſt ſweet and louing husband in the heauens, we muſt not ſettle vpon our lees, nor ſet our affections on things that are below, but follow on hard, though it be through the thorny path of perſecution, or the ſtrait way, that hee is gone before vs: wee muſt count all things but dunge and droſſe in reſpect of him. <hi>Phil.</hi> 7.8.</p>
                  <p>If any man would here know how wee muſt goe after Chriſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                     </label> the anſwere is, that we muſt doe it, firſt, by contemplation:
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by deſideration: thirdly, by determination: fourthly, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation or imitation. By contemplation wee euermore think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, and hauing our thoughts in heauen, where hee is. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18 By deſideration, wee euermore deſiring to be in his preſence, and to haue a fellowſhip with him in ioyes vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. <hi>Col.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. By determination, we euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more reſoluing with our ſelues, to cleaue continually to him, and to repute all things but traſh in reſpect of him. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.23. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.11. By conuerſation, or imitation, wee euermore labouring to doe as he hath done, and to walke in ſuch ſteps, as hee is gone before vs. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Math.</hi> 11.29. Oh my brethren, ſtriue and contend to follow Chriſt after theſe waves, if there be any thing, that will hinder you from the ſame, caſt it away. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. Be it that the right hand, or the right eye ſhould cauſe you to offend herein, yet ſpare them not cut off the one, and pull out the other. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.8.9. There are many Lords, doubtleſſe, ſtriuing for vs. The world with her pleaſures allures many to follow her, but pretend what ſhe will, in truth her word is <hi>Decipion,</hi> I will deceiue you. The fleſh would haue man a ſeruant to her luſts, ſhee wants not her baites wherewith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile him, but in truth her word is <hi>Inficiam,</hi> I will infect you. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, ſtrongeſt of the three, vſurpes ſuperiority ouer man, hee craues that man ſhould fall downe, and vvorſhip him, he vvante not promiſes enough, faire in ſhew, but in truth his word is <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiam,</hi> I will deſtroy you. Ieſus Chriſt our lawfull Lord bee alſo calls vpon vs, and exhorts vs to ſerue him, he hath life in the one hand, durable riches and honour in the other, and in truth his word is <hi>Reficiam,</hi> I will refreſh you.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:8504:48"/>
                  <p>Now in this ſtrife to vvhom ſhall vvee yeeld our ſelues, but vnto him, vvho cries <hi>Reficiam?</hi> Let vs therefore doe as vve are here vvilled for to doe; <hi>come away:</hi> and then doubtleſſe vvee ſhall vvant nothing. <hi>Habent enim omnia, qui habent Chriſtum habentem omnia:</hi> For they haue all vvho doe enioy Chriſt the Lord of all. And ſo I end, and commend you to God, and to the vvord of his grace, vvhich is able to build further and to giue you an inheritance among all them which are ſanctified. To the vvhich inheritance the Lord bring vs all for his ſonnes ſake, to vvhom vvith the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt, one eternall God, and three diſtinct perſons, be all honour, and glory aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed both novv and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8504:48"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
